good afternoon, dear listeners, colleagues,
добрый день уважаемые слушатели коллеги
friends, I am the dean of the faculty of financial
друзья я декан факультета финансовой
economics pogrebnyak evgeny
экономики погребняк евгений
, today I represent
я представляю сегодня
my colleagues, the authors of the digital
моих коллег авторов программы цифровые
finn program of the digital finance master's program,
финна магистерской программы цифровые
which for the first time this year
финансы которые в первый раз в этом году
is presented at our faculty,
представляется на нашем нашем факультете
a very rich program is
программа очень насыщенная
dedicated to three vectors of development of
посвящена трем вектором развития
finance and companies in this sector  finn tech
финансов и компаний это сектор финн тех
this is digital transformation
это цифровая трансформация
changing the financial function
изменение финансовой функции
changing how the finance
изменения того как работают финансовый
department and treasury work
отдел и казначейство
planning and economic departments in
планово-экономический департаменты в
corporations, this third direction
корпорациях вот это третье направление
seems to me the
мне кажется наиболее
most under-researched or not fully
не до исследованным что ли не до конца
disclosed and very important because these
раскрытым и очень важным потому что эти
changes in the finances of an enterprise
изменения в финансах предприятия
occur in  for all companies, it doesn’t matter if this is the
происходят во всех компаниях неважно это
financial sector or other sectors of the
финансовый сектор другие сектора
economy, and based on the relevance of
экономики и исходя из актуальности вот
this task for the digital finance sector,
этой задачи для сектора цифровых
we organized our current
финансов мы организовали наш текущий
round table, which is dedicated to the profession of a
круглый стол который посвящен профессии
digital financial director digital
цифрового финансового директора digital
sifu and today we want to learn from
сифу и сегодня мы хотим узнать от
practitioners about the relevance of this task in
практиков об актуальности этой задачи на
different industries in different combos in different industries in
скую в разных комбо разных индустриях в
different companies
разных компаниях
in different types of business how the
в разных видов бизнеса как меняется
profession of financial director is changing is there
профессий финансового директора
really a new
действительно ли появляется новая
digital component this is our first
цифровая составляющая это наш первый
question how it is seen from different
вопрос как это видится из разных
companies and the second is  how can we better
компаний а второе это как нам лучше
organize the training of students
организовать подготовку студентов для
so that they
того чтобы они смогли для того чтобы они
can better fit into the new reality
могли лучше вписаться в новую реальность
and become such agents of change in
и стали такими агентами изменений на
enterprises so that they already come with
предприятиях чтобы они уже пришли с
some new skills that are in
какими-то новыми навыками которые
demand in companies and their career, their
востребованы в компаниях и их карьера их
professional growth would be  thanks to
профессиональный рост был бы благодаря
this, even more quickly,
этому еще более быстро
I would like to give the floor to our
я бы хотел передать слово нашему
foreign guest,
зарубежному гостю
our friend john kibby housing gianluca
нашему другу джону кибби жилье джанлука
na financier by education engineer by
на финансист по образованию инженер по
other education worked in the
другому образованию работал в секторе ц
telecommunications sector in private
телекоммуникаций в фондах частных
investment funds in italy and the middle east
инвестиций в италии и на ближнем востоке
and is the founder of a start-up
и является основателем стартапа
in the field of financial
в области финансового моделирования
in addition to this,
возможности экселя помимо этого сейчас
Gianluca is actively consulting now, I would
джанлука активно консультирует я бы
like to ask him about the existence of
хотел его спросить о вообще наличие
such a profession,
такой профессии
does digital exist?
существует ли существует ли цифровой si
fa fa fa
fa fa fa fa fa fa fa fa
fa
fa
fa fa fa fa fa fa
fa fa fa fa fa fa
fa fa
fa fa
fa
fa
fa risk for without center banner and this is s
fa риску за без центр баннере а это s
beater &amp; free
beater &amp; free
soul
soul
[music]
[музыка]
at
при
sports palace im without
спорта им без
index
индекс
top
сверху
[music]
[музыка]
people &amp;
people &amp;
blogs
blogs
for
ибо
context
контекста
next
next
time
time
he is sponge
он спондж
yes
да
yes yes
да да
yes yes yes from calls
да да да от вызовов
herself and maria
самой а мария
buy for
buy for
infants and
infants and
work
work
on the story is no way here is your
on the story is no way вот твой
image
имидж
other
other
projects
projects
[music]
[музыка]
for
for
mobile
mobile
media
media
queries in
queries in
process
process
users
users
in excel and
in excel и
never
не
heard of writing problems  Gianluca from and about
слыхал писал проблем джанлука из и про
it hides models and runaways and
именно спрячет моделей и наутек and
excel here using excel at my life of a
excel вот using excel at my life of a
brief solved the models of the model
brief порешил модели модели
our next speech from our
наше следующее выступление от наших
colleagues from the
коллег из
nikon auditing company and he is
аудиторской компанией nikon и он это
Larisa Efremova Olga  Chumachenko, and in
лариса ефремова ольга чумаченко и в
preparation for this speech, it
подготовке к этому выступлению для меня
sounded very important and very
прозвучало очень важно и очень важный
important for me that the
момент что
need to digitalize the financial
необходимость цифровизации финансовой
function is never at all, yes, it’s
функции она никогда то вообще да что это
not not not yesterday not tomorrow, but it is in
не не не вчера не завтра а вот именно в
2022 that a
2022 году
very interesting case will be happy to
очень интересный кейс будем рады вас
listen to you
послушать
well now by connecting
хорошо сейчас подключаясь
colleagues, it’s nice to hear everyone, it’s a pity that we
коллеги приятно всех услышать жаль что
don’t really see everyone. 2022 has
не всех видим действительно 2022 год
become a very important digitalization system for us for Russia,
именно для нас для россии стал очень
which is connected with
системе цифровизации с чем это связано с
federal law
введен федеральный закон
125a in the Russian Federation on January 1, 22; accounting for rent, this
125а бухгалтерский учет аренды этот
standard was prepared on the basis of f-16  that
стандарт подготовлен на базе с f-16 то
is, for the first time in Russia, in order to reflect
есть впервые в россии чтобы отразить
some operations on financial and
какие-то операции по финансовой и
operating leases, they cannot
операционной аренде их нельзя будет
simply be taken from someone’s contract from
взять просто с кого-то договора с
some invoice invoice,
какой-то накладной счет-фактуры так
etc., but it will be necessary to make calculations
далее а надо будет произвести расчеты
for exactly what we need
именно для чего нам необходимо
digitalization for now we are on  example,
цифровизация сейчас мы на примере
we will show what calculations will need to be
покажем какие расчеты необходимо будет
done and the second moment
сделать и второй момент
for the first time in Russia  But in our
впервые в россии именно в нашем
Russian standard, emphasis is placed on the
российском стандарте сделан акцент на
mandatory use in Russia of the
обязательное применение в россии
international standard for calculating
международного стандарта по расчету
reserves for expected
резервов по ожидаемым
credit losses, this is mc under 9, directly
кредитным убыткам это mc под 9 прям
in the victory standard itself, this is indicated
самом стандарте победе это указан
if earlier registered with the lessor
если раньше на учете у арендодателя
if the accounting is based on the
если на базе учет ведется набор на
balance sheet of the lessor, then this is a fixed
балансе арендодателя то это основное
asset  a profitable investment is reflected in
средство доходное вложение отражается
income in the form of just for the flesh,
доход виде всего лишь за во плоти жа
there are no problems if the ball on the balance sheet of the
проблем нет если на бал на балансе
lessee then reflects interest
лизингополучателя то отражаются проценты
and the total cost of all lease
и общая стоимость всех лизинговых
payments is reflected in the same way on the
платежей отражается точно также
balance sheet, then from January 1, 22
бухгалтерском балансе то с 1 января 22
, everything has changed dramatically, what
года кардинально все изменилось что
is happening now in accordance with
сейчас происходит в соответствии
25 we must
25 мы должны
the moment at the earliest date to
момент на самую раннюю дату
qualify the contract is it a financial
квалифицировать договор это финансово
lease or operating paying attention
аренды или операционная обращая внимание
specifically to the
именно для
lessor there are certain functions the
арендодателя есть определенные функции
principles of financial rent I will literally
принципы финансовой ренты я и буквально
list a few others you
перечислю несколько остальные вы там
will see there in the presentation, first of all, if
увидите в презентации прежде всего если
at the end of the lease contract the right to
по окончании договора лизинга право
own  responsibility for the leased property
собственности на лизинговое имущество
passes to the
переходит
lessee this is a financial tape the
лизингополучателю это финансовая лента
second moment if the tenant has the right
второй момент если арендатор имеет право
to purchase the leased asset at the end of the
на покупку предмета аренды по окончании
contract at a cost much lower than the
договора по стоимости намного ниже
market value this is also a financial lease if
рыночной это тоже финансовая аренда если
the lease term
срок аренды
takes up a significant part of the period of
значительную часть занимает от срока
use of the equipment then this is also a
использования оборудования то это тоже
financial lease here in IFRS and  in
финансовая аренда вот в мсфо и в
Russian legislation, the word is
российском законодательстве слово стоит
significant, and if we turn to and with
значительны а если мы обратимся к и с
ready-made standards, then
готов ским стандартам то там написано
more than 75 percent are written there, we will also
более 75 процентов будем этого также
adhere to this if it is necessary to conclude an
придерживаться если надо сам заключении
agreement when we press about
договора когда мы пресс про
discounting cash flows, we
дисконтирование денежные потоки мы
will see that the discounting cost
увидим что стоимость дисконтирования
is practically equal to the cost where the market
равна практически стоимость где рыночной
object of lease  this is also a financial
предмета аренды это тоже финансовая
tape, practically this is again all with us
лента практически это опять все у нас
or zentsov or from Russia Gamovskoe's views are
или зенцов или из россии views гамовское
written more than 90 percent well, and the tenant has the
написано более 90 процентов ну и имеет
right to extend the contract at a
право продлить договор арендатор по
cost much lower than
стоимости намного ниже чем
if he had simply accepted this contract
если бы просто он принимал этот договор
zero and this subject l  I just
ноль и этот предмет лизинга просто
bought leasing and that it comes from tires for the first time
покупал а чтоб исходит из шин впервые у
we understand the concept of such
нас понимаю понятие такой
discounting of cash flows the
дисконтирование денежных потоков
effective rate was not previously in Russian
эффективная ставка раньше в российских
standards and this is only
стандартов это не было и это только
true with the help of anti-technologies
действительно с помощью анти технологий
when we determined that this
когда мы с вами определили что эта
financial lease from the lessor is
финансовая аренда у лизингодателя это
reflected in the balance sheet as  net
отражается в балансе как чистые
investment in rent and income is in the
инвестиции в аренду и доход происходит в
form of interest if these indicators are not
виде процентов если эти показатели не
met, the signs that you list,
выполняются признаки которым перечисли
then this is an operating lease and income is
то это операционная аренда и доход
recognized evenly over the entire
признается равномерно в течение всего
lease term, but the cost of all all
срока аренды попку стоимость все всех
lease payments and here we are
лизинговых платежей и вот мы
returning the same value of
возвращаемся уже тоже такой стоимость
net investment in rent yes  we have a
чистых инвестиций в аренду да у нас есть
gross investment
валовые инвестиции
that includes all leasing flows,
которая включает все лизинговые потоки
plus for the first time again in Russian
плюс впервые опять звучит в российском
legislation there is a non-guaranteed
законодательстве не гарантированная
liquidation value,
ликвидационная стоимость
this is the cost at which we can
эта стоимость по которой мы сможем
sell the leased asset at the end
продать предмет аренды по окончании
of the lease agreement, for example, at the end of the
договора лизинга например по окончании
agreement, the cost of a truck will be
договора стоимость грузовика будет
cost 100,000 why not guaranteed
стоить 100000 почему не гарантировано
yet unknown sell and or not we
еще неизвестно продадим и или нет мы
take the net gross investment
берем баловать чистый валовые инвестиции
in the lease discounted at the effective
в аренду дисконтируем в эффективной
rate and find the net investment in the
ставки и находим чистую инвестицию в
lease that is, the question arises what
аренду то есть возникает вопрос что
is a fictitious rate
такое фиктивная ставка
what is discounting and what is
что такое дисконтирование и что такое
cash flow and all this is done with
денежные потоки и все это делается с
With the help of special programs
помощью специальных программ
, our requirements for the application of
вот возникает наши требования применения
encef 9 arise, we must definitely conduct a
энцефа 9 мы обязательно должны проводить
test for the depreciation of net investments in
тест на обесценение чистых инвестиций в
rent. This is a whole topic that is very interesting.
аренду это целая тема очень интересная
simulate
смоделировать
what is the expected credit loss and
что такое ожидаемо кредитной убытки и
will pay the client will not pay us when he
заплатит не заплатит нам клиент когда
pays what amount what kind of losses
заплатит какой сумме какой какие убытки
we will incur and so on there is a possibility of
мы понесем и так далее есть вероятность
bankruptcy or not and as a rule this is the
банкротства или нет и как правило это
minimum you need to do a divorce but all
минимум надо делать развод но все
companies do this at least
компании делают минимум это
quarterly
ежеквартально
h  then it happens with the lessee the lessee’s o rn
что происходит у арендатора о р н
it is very important no matter what
это очень важно не важно какая
operating or financial lease
операционная или финансовая аренда
there will always be the right to use the
всегда в балансе будет право пользования
assets and liabilities in the balance sheet where the
активам и обязательствам в балансе где
liabilities are not in vain it is 16 on the basis of
обязательства ведь не зря это 16 на базе
which facebook 25 was prepared in
которого подготовлен facebook 25 в
Europe was accepted for 10 years why
европе принимался 10 лет почему потому
because  even if this operating lease,
что даже если эта операционная аренда
as a rule, these were aircraft, then all the
как правило это были самолеты то все
same, the obligations had to be reflected, and
равно обязательства надо было отражать и
from this immediately all the cavenants for
от этого сразу все кавенанты по
obtaining credit funds from us, to put
получению кредитных средств у нас мягко
it mildly, flew away from it, so for a very long time this
говоря летели от поэтому очень долго это
standard was adopted in just two words,
стандарт принимался буквально два слова
I want to say it can be
хочу сказать можно
excluded not to apply this standard
исключить не применять этот стандарт вот
here there are three cases when you can not
здесь есть три случая когда можно не
apply, but these cases, as a rule, they
применять но эти случаи они как правило
practically do not fit, because
практически не подходят потому что у нас
now, even in Russian
сейчас даже в российском
legislation, it happens when the
законодательстве происходит при
economic form is over the
обладаний экономической формы над
content
содержанием
, once very many years ago, ten years ago
когда-то очень много лет назад лет
it was necessary to register a
десять надо было регистрировать договор
special real estate lease agreement
аренды недвижимости специальных
state bodies  and therefore, in order not to
госорганах и поэтому чтобы его не
register it, companies entered
регистрировать компании заключали
into an agreement for 11 months and extended it
договор на 11 месяцев и продлевали в
for ten years, and now the
течение десяти лет да вот сейчас
companies also have to say
компании также приходится говорят что
that it’s not the only one for months, I fall under
вот он не один с месяцев я попадаю под
exceptions for it, the application of this
исключения на нее применение этого
standard will not work, so you and I should
стандарта не пойдет так мы с вами должны
see if  optional if
посмотреть если опционным если права на
we can extend the rights or about after all and so
продление можем или про ведь и так далее
on under what conditions and anyway we
на каких условиях и все равно мы
accept the right to use the axioms
принимаем право пользования аксиом
because the exception does not fit the second
потому что исключение не подходит второй
moment the cost of the standard is reflected is
момент стоимость стандарте отражена это
300 thousand I draw your attention to 300000
300 тысяч обращаю ваше внимание 300000
this should be the cost
это а должна быть стоимость
initially these residuals with us  300
первоначально эти остаточные у нас 300
thousand and the cost, let's say an ATM, it
тысяч а стоимость допустим банкомат это
cost a million, that means the exception is also
стоило миллион то значит исключение тоже
not suitable, and if there is an exception on the simplified system
не подходит и если на упрощенной системе
3, but here you also need to
3 исключение но здесь тоже надо
look if the
посмотреть если переходит право
ownership of the property is transferred if it is
собственности на имущество если сдается
subleased, the exception
в субаренду тоже исключение применить
cannot be applied, so we have come to the conclusion
нельзя поэтому мы с вами пришли к выводу
that a large  part must apply for 25
что большая часть должны применять по 25
and we are with you  we start with the fact that we
и мы с вами начинаем с того что мы
determine the obligations of the guy
определяем обязательства парень
with the contract and we don’t see it, take the
с договором и не это не видим взять
numbers ready from the invoice, we can’t we
цифры готова из накладной мы не можем мы
have to calculate all this with you, that is,
должны с вами все это посчитать то есть
we must
мы должны
determine at the sight of the present
определить при виде приведенная
value of future foam, here
стоимость будущих пенных вот здесь
such a moment arises if this is a
возникает такой момент если это
financial lease  there and the solution
финансовая аренда там и р-р посчитать
is calculated very quickly, and if we allow the building
очень быстро а если это допустим здание
to use the building in our case, well,
срока использования здания у нас деле ну
let's say we took it for five years, and the building itself has
допустим мы взяли на пять лет а само
been used for 50 years, or there is 30
здание используется 50 лет или там 30
effective rate, as a rule, there is no effective rate in the
эффективной ставки как правило в
contract and no one orders you and
договоре нет и никто тебе не указ и еще
also  cost must be calculated fair
и стоимость надо посчитать справедливый
.  that is, it’s also unrealistic for me to hire an
. то есть я тоже нереально нанимать и
appraiser so
оценщика для того чтобы
that we can give examples here,
этому мы вот я здесь привожу примеры
you can apply the rate using the
можно применить ставку используя
statistical bulletin of the Bank of Russia, that
статистический бюллетень банка россии то
is, under what conditions
есть на каких условиях
is a loan issued
а выдается кредит
for exactly these terms with such and such
под именно вот эти сроки с такими-то
requirements, and so on we apply this
требованиями и так далее применяем эту
rate  we discount lease payments and
ставку дисконтируем лизинговые платежи и
rent and find the
рентные и находим обязательства по
lease obligations, we found the lease obligations,
аренде нашли мы повязать из об аренде
well done, but you and I need to determine
молодцы но нам с вами надо определить
all the rights to use the asset, and it
все права пользования активом а в него
also adds, in addition to the lease obligation, the
еще добавляется кроме обязательства по
advance payments that you
аренде авансовые платежи который вы
paid earlier, the costs
заплатили раньше затраты которые
associated with the acquisition of the leased asset
связанные с приобретением предмета
, well  let's say
аренды ну допустим
we bought some kind of mill and we need to
мы купили какой то стану и мы должны его
bring it to a state in order to use
довести до состояния чтобы использовать
it, that is, the adjustment of this machine, the
то есть наладка этого станка
estimated obligation to dismantle,
оценочное обязательство по демонтажом ну
for example, the simplest example is a drilling
например самый простой пример буровую
rig we leased a parkour or a
установку взяли в лизинг паркуре или
well, we need to do the installation of this
скважину мы должны где монтаж этой
rig and that's just the
установки сделать и вот как раз
last moment  it's still to bring the
последний момент это еще довести
recovery  The change in the environment
восстановление окружающей среды до того
before you started this indicates that
как вы начали это говорит о том что
there is a formation,
происходит формирование
first of all, of an obligation that
прежде всего обязательства которое
is associated with discounting cash
связано с дисконтирование денежных
flows and then the
потоков и далее
right to use assets and liabilities
право пользования активы и обязательства
lives their own lives separately because
живёт своей жизнью отдельно потому что
we extinguish obligations depending on
обязательства мы гасим в зависимости от
our lease payments, that is, the
наших лизинговых платежей то есть
lease payment  is divided into two parts
лизинговый платеж делится на две части
, repayment of the principal debt and interest
гашение основного долга и проценты
that we will pay, and depreciation the
который мы будем платить а амортизация
right to use if the
право пользования если переходит право
ownership of this asset is transferred, then by the
собственности на этот актив то по
term of use if the
сроку использование если право
ownership is not transferred by the term of the
собственности не переходят по сроку
contract, I want to focus your
договора я хочу акцентировать ваше
attention on what is really with the
внимание что действительно именно с
input from this standard which  have
вводом от этого стандарта которую долго
been waiting for a long time which really
очень ждали который действительно
shows the economic essence of the
показывает экономическую суть
investment essence of the financial lease,
инвестиционную суть финансовой аренды
this has led to the fact that
этот него привело к тому что сейчас
now many companies are installing
очень многие компании устанавливают
various of
различные
these technologies in order
эти технологии по для того чтобы именно
for these lease payments to
вот эти лизинговые платежи сразу
be immediately calculated  but purely investments in
рассчитывались на чисто инвестиций в
rent, that is, grain companies and for the
аренду и то есть зерновые компании и на
right to use, first obligations,
право пользования сначала обязательства
then the right to use from other
потом право пользования у других
companies, and since
компаний а так как у нас
most of our country is still engaged in
большая часть страны все-таки занимается
renting, this standard is important for everyone
арендой то этот стандарт важен для всех
if there are any questions, I’m ready for
если есть какие то вопросы я готова на
them  answer now or later in the chat, as
них сейчас ответить или позже в чате как
you like,
угодно
aware of the wedding is a very interesting case
aware свадебного очень интересный кейс
for the fact that which shows that
для того что который показывает что
before the digital endorse something in
прежде чем цифра визировать что-то
finance, you need to understand how it works
финансах нужно понимать как это работает
even before digitalization, what
еще до цифровизации то о чем говорил
Gianluca was talking about understands the meaning and
джанлука понимает смысл и
final value of what we are doing to me
итоговую ценность того что мы делаем мне
it seems a great illustration here is
кажется прекрасная иллюстрация вот наши
our theses I know that olga has a
нашим тезисов я знаю что у ольги есть
presentation on how I will teach it
презентация по тому как это буду учить
olga chumachenko is ready yes colleagues good
ольга чумаченко готовы да коллеги добрый
afternoon you know again I would like
день еще раз знаете я бы хотелось
to start the presentation with the fact
презентацию начать с того что
that we have a great opportunity to
у нас есть прекрасная возможность
show how
показать насколько
much the specialty that is now in demand will be
востребована будет специальность которая
it is
сейчас ему
announced and dedicated to this
анонсируется и посвящено этой
specialty our master's program in
специальности магистратуре наша встреча
here is everything that we
вот все то что сейчас мы
have heard now, seen in the presentation, in
слышали видели в презентацию на самом
fact, this is all
деле это все
being done, this is all being implemented,
выполняется это все реализуется в том
including by young specialists
числе молодыми специалистами
who come to our company with
которые приходят в нашу компанию имея
knowledge of
знания по
finance, of course, she is very
финансам конечно она очень
interested in specialists who
заинтересованная в специалисты которые
will have knowledge in order to
будут обладать знаниями для того чтобы
then in practice  colleagues, tell me
затем в практике коллеги подскажите мне
please, I can show my presentation right now, the
пожалуйста я могу сейчас презентацию
organizers are
организаторы
fine,
отлично
let's say straight out that we
давайте будем говорить прямо что у нас
have a common task, this is the answer to the question of
есть общая задача это ответ на вопрос
how we need and what to teach our
как же нам нужно и чему научить наших
young specialist what competencies are in
молодой специалист какие компетенции
demand in this case in our
востребованы в данном случае в нашей
company we are the largest logical
компании мы самая крупная логической
Russian  company
российская компания
let's talk about it
давайте поговорим об этом
[music]
[музыка]
first, based on and relying on the
первое вот основываясь и опираясь на
presentation of vladimir, of course, this is the ability to
презентацию владимир конечно это умение
conduct an analysis based on empirical
проводить анализ на основе эмпирических
means, this means that it is necessary
значит это такое это значит что нужно
that a young specialist had
что в молодой специалист обладал
deep knowledge of basic deep
глубокими знаниями базовым глубоким
knowledge of financial tax accounting
знанием финансовые налогового учета
master's  programs they include
магистерские программы они включаются
such
такие
sections such courses but this is
разделы такие курсы но этого
not enough because a developed soskin
недостаточно потому что развитый соскин
with which is focused primarily on the
с которой ориентирована прежде всего на
development strategy of this company in
стратегию развития этой компании в
which you work and given the
которой вы работаете и учитывая
main trend associated with the
основной тенденцией связанные с
digitalization of financial departments,
цифровизации финансовых подразделений
what kind of knowledge, in our opinion, is most in
какие же знания на наш взгляд наиболее
demand, of course, this is primarily
востребованы конечно это прежде всего
advanced  the level of knowledge is one s.a.
продвинутый уровень знаний один с.а.
you need to strive to ensure that
нужно стремиться к тому чтобы эти знания
you have this knowledge you have two years
у вас были у вас есть два года для того
to complete the training and
чтобы пройти обучение и
practically it is necessary because
практически это необходимо потому что
this is the main basic level for the work of
это основной базовый уровень для работы
financial acquisition of course now there are
финансовых обретения конечно сейчас
such global changes in
такой глобальные изменения в
accounting and you need to understand
бухгалтерском учете и нужно понимать
some reasons why these  treason
причины какие то почему эти измене
is being introduced, such pragmatics exist at the
вводится такая существует прагматика на
current moment when implementing, of
текущий момент при внедрении
course, we must understand that if there is a
безусловно мы должны понимать что если
cowardly specificity, that is, we expect
трусливая специфика то есть мы ожидаем
that a
что
specialist who comes to us could
приходящий к нам могли специалиста они
clearly realize that those changes that
четко осознаю что те изменения которые
you take into account are taking place, they still
вы глазкам учете происходит они еще
have industry specifics, do not
имеют отраслевую специфику не земля не
forget the earth and we  we would recommend
забывать и мы бы рекомендовали
just the same through the prism of
вот как раз таки через призму
what federal standards exist for very much
чему на очень что существуют федеральные
accounting Russian and
стандарты вылазка учета российские и
international financial reporting standards
международные стандарты финансовой
here are the issues of convergence where we are now
вот вопросы сближения где мы сейчас
what are our main problems
находимся какие у нас основные проблемы
all this is very much in demand in many
все это очень востребована во многих
large companies in the audit
крупных компаниях аудиторских
industry and of course  we expect from young
отраслевых и конечно мы ждем от молодых
professionals the
специалистов
ability to conduct a
умения знаний навыков проводить
qualitative analysis based on the obtained
качественный анализ на основе полученных
financial indicators,
финансовые показатели
that is, not only to understand what they
то есть не просто понимать что они себя
are, but also to understand that on their
представляет но также понимать что на их
basis it is possible to carry out very high-quality
основе можно провести очень качественно
financial accounting caught up with
финансовый догнали
tax accounting of course tax accounting
налоговый учет конечно налоговый учет
financial accounting are closely
финансовый учет тесными строить
interconnected and short  I will say that
взаимосвязаны и коротко скажу что
you know financial accounting, so you need
знаете финансовый учет значит нужно
to understand at least the basic basis for
понимать хотя бы базовая основа к
tax accounting, it is very important to develop
налоговому учету очень важно развивать
yourself the so-called very popular
себе так называемая очень востребованную
large company sap skills, well, firstly,
крупная компания sap skills ну во первых
you need to be able to work in a team, the
надо уметь работать в команде
basic principles and orpheus of
основные принципы и орфею работы в
teamwork, what is focus, the result is
команде что такое нацеленность результат
very important time is needed  to understand
очень важно тайма нужно понимать когда
when I would say so time management is the
что я бы так сказал тайм-менеджмент это
basis for the development of a young specialist
основа развития молодого специалиста
corporate culture the
корпоративная культура
concept of subordination, all these
понятие субординации вот все эти как
seemingly important principles are generally understandable,
казалось бы важные общем понятные
but they are important for an employer
принципы но они важны для работодателя
when he decides to
когда он принимает решение о
cooperate with a young  specialists
сотрудничестве с молодым специалистам
as a young specialist to achieve the
как молодому специалисту достичь
required level of competence, but
необходимого уровня компетенции но
let's say straight out that we all
давайте будем говорить прямо что все мы
now live in an era of great change and
сейчас живем в эпоху больших перемен и
only continuous acquisition of new
только непрерывное получение новых
knowledge in order to improve
знаний в целях совершенствования
professional chicks can be two
профессиональной птенцы может быть двумя
ways - self-education and let the area
пути это самообразование и пусть площади
in exile
в эмиграции
which program helps to reach the
какие программы помогает достичь
required level  then competencies knowledge of
необходимо уровне то компетенции знание
excel knowledge of 1c, attention to the
excel знание 1с по внимание
relevance of the complex issues of introducing
актуальности сложных вопросов внедрения
new Russian
новых стандартов российской
accounting standards in the twentieth year, of course, you need
учета в двадцатом году конечно нужно
to understand the issues related to the introduction of
понимать вопросы связанные с внедрением
new and IFRS
новых и мсфо
financial analysis and those issues that
финансовый анализ и и те вопросы которые
I considered in the owl skills section
я рассматривала в разделе сов skills
on my part, I’ll probably be
с моей стороны наверное сейчас всю буду
glad now  to answer questions if they have
рада ответить на вопросы если они есть
colleagues,
коллеги
in
собственно
fact, continuous professional development gives us the opportunity through self-education advanced training courses to reach this level in order for us to have some kind of rapid introduction of
стоит какая-то быстрое внедрение
digitalization in the financial  division
цифровизация в финансовое подразделение
olives questions
оливки вопросы
quite a big thank you, it seems to me
довольно большое спасибо мне кажется
a very specific, clearly formulated
очень такой конкретный четко оформленные
request for
запрос на
highly qualified
высококвалифицированных
employees and indeed this
сотрудников и действительно вот эта
adaptation understanding of subordination
адаптация понимание субординации
understanding of how teams work in 1 of their
понимание как работают команды в 1 их
corporate cultures really
корпоративных культурах действительно
only through practice we can instill
только через практику можем привить
we will be glad to develop cooperation with
будем рады развить сотрудничество с вами
you and by the way with  clients of your
и ну и кстати с клиентами вашей
auditing company in order for our
аудиторской компании для того чтобы наши
students to take root there,
студенты там прижились осиба большое
thank you very much for marrying the speech, I want
спасибо за замуж за выступление я хочу
to give the floor to Yulia Yanina, this is our
передать слово юлии яниной это наша наша
colleague, a teacher, a person who is
коллега преподаватель человек который
already facing
уже сейчас сталкивается с
our specific bachelor's my and
нашими конкретными бакалавра my и
master's programs, we have experience teaching
магистрами у нас есть опыт преподавания
in the
на
master's program  the economy go
магистерской программе экономика идти
here Yulia asked him to share but
вот юлия попросил его поделиться но
such practical
такими практическими
considerations
соображениями
as Yulia looks to you but
как юля тебе выглядит но представляется
digitalization seems to be based on your
цифровизация в исходя из твоего
practical experience as a financial
практического опыта как финансового
professional and
профессионала и
well, what can we give new to ours
ну что мы можем дать нового нашим нашим
students
студентам
good afternoon everyone can’t
добрый день всем как не слышно
hear yes yes harmless on this I loved
слышно да да безобидно на таком я любил
yes
да
hello from the crimea if july can
привет из крыма если июля а может
include a presentation because I have
включить презентацию потому что меня
a small technical problem here
здесь небольшая техническая проблема
there was a blockage thanks I completely
возникла блокировки спасибо я полностью
agree with the previous
согласна с предыдущим
speaker with olga
докладчиком с ольгой
in general, now there is a big
в общем то сейчас идет большая
trend  on the automation of everyone on
тенденция на автоматизацию всех на
their knees, including
колени деятельность в том числе
financial services, the next slide
финансовых служб можно следующий слайд
answers the question posed by the
отвечает на поставленный вопрос
profession in general, a financier,
профессии вообще финансист
we can safely say that financiers and
мы смело можем говорить что финансисты и
specialists with knowledge of finance
специалисты обладающие знанием финансах
can work in different industries, ranging
могут работать в разных отраслях начиная
from banking and somewhere to
от банкинга и где-то до
automation in IT information
автоматизации в информационных
companies  in companies, this profession
компаниях айти компаниях эта профессия
will always be in demand; it changes
всегда будет востребованной оно меняется
in response to what is happening in the world.
в ответ на то что происходит в мире
financial specialists help
специалисты по финансовому помогают
companies calculate
компаниям рассчитывать
rice and, by reducing the number of
рис и сокращая сокращать количество
costs, increase the payback of the product and,
издержек повышать окупаемость продукт и
most importantly, pay your losses
самое главное обратите на свои убытки
at least to see what is in general.
хоть в просмотреть что вообще
means the profession of a financier at the
подразумевает профессия финансист на
current moment, that is, that personnel
текущий момент то есть что кадровые
services are requesting in search of such a
службы запрашивают в поисках такого
specialist, first of all,
специалиста во первых конечно должны
our students would have to understand club bachelors of
понимать наши студенты бы club бакалавры
magistracy who come to learn how
магистратуры кто приходит обучаться как
to read financial statements how to
читать финансовую отчетность как
compile them know and analog
составлять ее знать и аналоговый
accounting
бухгалтерский учет
regulatory framework federal laws
нормативную базу федеральные законы
relating to this area of
касающиеся этого направления
also be able to have skills have skills
также уметь навыки иметь навыки
financial modeling i.e.
финансовое моделирование то есть
predict business development
прогнозировать развитие бизнеса
calculate different indicators
рассчитывать разные показатели
possible risks identify know the office
возможные риски выявлять знайте офисной
program even better if a specialist
программы еще лучше если специалист
knows how to program at least at a basic
умеет программировать хотя бы на базовом
level
уровне например для финансиста вообще
their data needs
сталкиваться большие данные их нужно
to be visualized somehow
как-то визуализировать
in order to see the dynamics and
для того чтобы смотреть динамику и
react in time, the business reacted to
вовремя реагировать бизнес реагировал на
certain
определенные
situations that occur in business,
ситуации которая происходит бизнесе
as well as
также
financiers who are involved in this
финансисты кто занимается этим
direction in general, in principle, should
направлением вообще в принципе должен
have great
обладать огромной
erudition in the field of economics to know the
эрудиции в в области экономики знать
specifics of the business with which it works,
специфику бизнеса с которой он работает
that is, the market
то есть рынок
and in general how the business works, all the schemes,
и вообще как устроен бизнес все схемы и
and our financial services always
вот наши финансовые службы всегда
understand very thoroughly the
разбирается в очень досконально в
details of the business, that is, financiers
деталях бизнеса то есть финансисты
understand all attacked
разбираются во всех напали
no  business, in order to be able to communicate with different departments both
нет бизнеса для того чтобы и
from a financial point of view and from a non-automation point of view,
с финансовой точки зрения и с точки
that is,
разными департаментом то есть навыки
communication
коммуникации
skills,
навыки
initiative skills should be manifested by such
инициативности должна проявляться таких
specialists, that is, such general
специалистов то есть такие общие
general skills that, in general, are
общее скиллы которые в общем-то для
typical for many, the
многие характерные
next slide is
следующий слайд он
now based on  trends that are
сейчас исходя из тенденций который
generally taking place in the world and in Russia,
вообще происходит в мире и в россии
in general, four
вообщем то можно выделить четыре
directions for the development of this profession can be distinguished: this is a
направления развития этой профессии это
financier economist analyst
финансист экономист аналитик
we have a manager and a financier engineer
нас есть менеджер и финансист инженер
here it is interesting that the line between them is very
здесь интересно грань между ними очень
thin and
тонко и
often there is a combination of
часто идет совмещение
such specialists, but as I said and
таких специалистов но как я сказала и
as Olga also said  that we have, but the
как ольга тоже говорилось что у нас но
financial sector is very extensive, that is, you
финансовая сфера очень обширна то есть
have to delve into various different
приходится углубляться в разное разное
details, for example, a financier economist,
детали например финансист экономист
he analyzes financial indicators,
он анализирует финансовые показатели
respectively, we must give such
соответственно мы должны дать такие
knowledge to our listeners, that is, you know how to
знания и нашим слушателям то есть умеете
analyze the financial indicators of the
анализировать финансовые показатели
market, evaluate the value of a company's
рынке оценивать стоимость компании
financial instruments and assets,
финансовых инструментов и активов
predict I macro economically
прогнозировать я макр экономически
they show
показывают
[music]
[музыка]
and the
а
economist he develops a strategy since
экономист он разрабатывает стратегию раз
these companies improve the furnace company the
эти компании улучшает компанец печи вает
analyst looks at various indicators
аналитик смот разные показатели
analyzes the risks of the father an interesting
анализирует риски отце интересное
direction of the financial engineer here is
направление финансово инженера вот
this communication specialist here with our
этот специалист связи вот с нашими
changes in information technology of
изменениями в информационных технологиях
huge automation which is now
огромной автоматизации который сейчас
happening
происходит
financial engineer to design new
инженер финансовые конструировать новые
financial instruments and  products, that
финансовые инструменты и продукты то
is, he analyzes financial markets,
есть он анализирует финансовые рынки
trends, looks for some optimal
тренды ищет какие-то оптимальные
sources of financing for corporations,
источники финансирования для корпораций
and
и
in general, financial
в общем то в последнее время финансовые
markets have recently undergone huge car  dynamic
рынки претерпели огромные кардинальные
changes such new
изменения появились такие новые
information financial technologies as
информационные финансовые технологии как
blockchain crowd finca appeared and then
блокчейн крауд финкой и тогда ли
electronic payments with all these
электронные платежи вот вот этими всеми
products i.e. the development of new
продуктами то есть разработка новых
similar
подобных
products is occupied by a financial engineer a
продуктов занимает финансовый инженер
financial manager analyzes this
финансовый менеджер анализирует данная
risk the company needs to
рисков компания потребности в компании
raise capital assesses the value of the
привлечения капитала оценивает стоимость
business organizes control over
бизнеса организует контроль над
investments and
инвестициями и
the financial manager takes part in the
финансовый менеджер принимает участие в
preparation of the company's budget system
подготовке системы бюджетов компании
participates in the modeling of the financial
участвует в моделирование финансовом
evaluation of the effectiveness of investment projects,
оценка эффективности инвестпроектов
that is, the financier must keep pace with
то есть финансиста должен идти в ногу с
automation in step with the times and
автоматизацией в ногу со временем и
here the next slide please now there
здесь следующий слайд пожалуйста сейчас
is a huge transformation,
идет огромнейшая трансформация в том
including the
числе и
financial sector and, for example, according
финансовой сферы и например по
to RBC development research  The financial
исследованиям рбк развитии финансовой
industry is heading in such directions as
индустрии идет по таким направлениям как
innovation in digital currencies i.e.
инноваций в цифровых валютах то есть
blockchain technology is causing a number of
технология блокчейн вызывает ряд
huge changes aimed at
огромных изменений направлена на
the aaa
а
space i.e. over the past b  the
пространство то есть за последние будет
number of transactions
заметно увеличивается количество сделок
related to cryptocurrency will noticeably increase, we are
связанных с криптовалютой нас
forming some such
формируется некоторые такие платформы
credit card platforms as an additional
карты кредита качестве дополнительного
incentive
стимула
, another direction is without
еще одно направление это без
contact, that is, according to the
контактность то есть по данным
central bank, for example, in
центрального банка например в
2023, the turnover of cash and
2023 году оборот наличных и на
will decrease a
сократится
big push to
большой толчок
abandon real money cinnamon go to
отказу от живых денег корицы выйти на
remotely change  your childish experience of
дистанционно менять свой детский опыт
communication with the requirements
связи с требованиями
[music]
[музыка]
very service
очень сервис
me
меня
it's only me or
это только у меня или
echo probably only you sometimes
эхо наверное только у тебя иногда
interrupting understandable
прерываясь понятно
maybe
возможно
she can please you list
ей можно просьба вас список финн
technology finn read and agree
технологии прочитали и согласны
two words students here's what you
два слова студентах вот что тебя
what you in them but maybe that  -somehow
что тебя в них но может быть что-то
unexpectedly or vice versa once you
неожиданно или наоборот вот когда-то
communicate with students what you need to know
общаешься со студентами что нужно знать
about our students
о наших студентов
well what you need to know about our students
ну что нужно знать о нашем студентах
our students still lack
нашим студентам все-таки не хватает
basic no skills exactly
базовых никаких навыков именно
financial
финансового
instruments people often come to the registry ben
регистратуру часто приходят люди бен
add that master of education yes yes
добавлять что магистр образования да да
Yes
да
yes, we start from the base,
да мы начинаем с базы
how it is built, how to
как она строится как ее
analyze it
анализировать
[music]
[музыка]
and
и
financial indicators in general, that is,
вообще финансовые показатели то есть вот
in my opinion,
на мой взгляд
undergraduate students
студентам
in the master's program are not enough
бакалавриате в магистратуре не хватает
well
ну
[music]
[музыка]
all all the guys are always proactive, they
все все ребята всегда инициативные очень
work very well at lectures and at
хорошо работают на лекциях и на
seminars, that is, now  a portrait of a
семинарах то есть сейчас портрет
modern student is
современного студента
very, very put
очень-очень положить
everyone is interested in his knowledge,
все заинтересованы в его знаниях
they work out completely all the tasks
они отрабатывают полностью все задачи
that are set for them, that is
которые перед ними ставится то есть
, they work, you can say students who
работают можно сказать студентов которые
would be interested in us
бы мне было бы интересно нас
presentation of trends and
представление трендов и
our current
нашего текущего
understanding of what students know and
представления о том что студенты знают и
should learn
должны узнать
thank you very much I would like to pass the
спасибо большое я бы хотел передать
floor to Irina the same to be honest
слово ирине одинаковой если честно
several times I didn’t really
несколько раз я так не то чтобы
shudder, but noted for myself the
вздрогнул но отметил для себя
speeches of previous colleagues references to the
выступлениях предыдущих коллег ссылки на
study of
исследование крупных консалтинговых
large consulting companies  derov information,
компаний крупных провайдеров информации
irina just represents such a
ирина как раз представляет такого
major player in the market
крупного игрока рынка
of the acc steam company, this is accenture
компании акк steam это accenture
accenture in russia, besides this
accenture в россии кроме кроме этого
company, accenture is a
компании accenture является
strategic and long-term partner of the
стратегическим и давним партнером
company;
компании стала то холдинга с 8 капитал
visits to offsite events and
визитах выездных выездных мероприятиях и
the question itself is rather not the same as
собственно вопрос скорее не тот же что и
for the rest yes how do you see the
к остальным да как вам видится
digitalization of the financial function
цифровизация финансовой функции
have you seen live digital financial
видели ли вы живьём цифровых финансовых
directors
директоров
what they are now what they will be in the
какие они сейчас какие они будут в
future and what we can give students
будущем и что нам дать студентам
yes thank you very much
да спасибо большое колени
knees really really  interesting questions, and
на самом деле очень интересные вопросы а
julia, I can ask you,
юля можно просить вас
in fact, all the largest companies
на самом деле все крупнейшие компании
here in
здесь в россии
russia all over the world have long and persistently
во всем мире уже давно и упорно
moved towards the fact that finances become
движутся к тому чтобы финансы стали
digital and the
цифровыми и
role of the safe, which, well, probably,
роль сейфа что ну наверное тоже важно
will also be important for students from such a financier who is rather
будет для студентов от такого скорее
close to an accountant.
близкого к бухгалтеру
there counter  they are olating
финансисту которой ну там контролируют
who, at the reporting date, prepares a report,
который на отчетную дату готовит отчет
shows yes, there are some indicators,
показывает да там какие-то показатели
let’s say, of the past, yes,
скажем так прошлого прошлого да
moves towards the fact that the
движется к тому что сифа финансовый
CFO becomes a business partner,
директор становится бизнес-партнером
becomes a strategic one and your cheese
становятся стратегическим и твой сыром
for business allows business to
для бизнеса позволяет бизнесу принимать
make certain decisions and the gap between
те или иные решения и пропасть между
traditional finances  if you
традиционными финансами вот если
look at the slide in the left corner and
посмотреть на слайда в левом углу и
call it a legend file from this is what
называем это legend файл из это к чему
in fact all the large corporations are already
на самом деле все крупные корпорации уже
moving towards and here Russia is everywhere in the world
движется и и здесь россии везде в мире
it is huge and it is here that when
она огромная и именно здесь при
possessing prior construction and digital
обладании до построения и цифровых
finance this is what we call
финансов это то что мы называем
intelligence files
intelligence файлы
the ability to make informed
возможность принимать обоснованные
decisions quickly
решения быстро
arises much faster that's what
возникает гораздо быстрее вот на чем
you can work on in order to build
можно работать для того чтобы построить
digital finance here on this slide there
цифровые финансы здесь на этом слайде
are several let's say even a
представлены несколько скажем даже
few parameters on which the
несколько параметров над которыми
organization of work is up to 1 frame and yes, what is
организации работы до 1 кадр и да то что
called the body of the
называется тела
hay state and here are other colleagues too
штат сена и и вот другие коллеги тоже об
they talked about it yes that is a fact  Technically, the
этом говорили да то есть фактически
financial service now consists not
финансовая служба сейчас состоит не
only of
только из
financiers and accountants,
финансистов и бухгалтеров
here we need specialists predictive
здесь нужны специалисты предиктивные
analysts dat ass on this you are modelers,
аналитики dat ass on this ты моделисты
that is, those who know how to build
то есть те кто умеет строить
predictive models who know how to evaluate
предикативные модели кто умеет оценивать
business cases and give business advice,
бизнес кейсы и давать бизнесу совет
for example, a folder not to invest
например складыватель не вкладывать в
in a particular project, that is  Let's just say that the
тот или иной проект то есть скажем так
interest for the same applicants is that what the
интерес для тех же абитуриентов того что
financial service does is much wider
делает финансовая служба гораздо шире
than what is much wider than accounting is
того что гораздо шире бухгалтерии
much wider than reporting, this is natural,
гораздо шире отчетности это естественно
but the analysis of what business goes to and what it does
но анализ того до бизнес идет и что он
naturally is the appropriate
делать естественно это соответствующие
discipline, these are the appropriate
дисциплина это соответствующие
appropriate roles and the
соответствующие роли и
study of relevant data
изучении соответствующих данных
materials, as for  well, yes, of
материалов то что касается бей то да
course, digital financially based
естественно цифровые финансово основаны
on data is
на данных
clear to everyone, and it is data and the
всем понятно и и именно данные и
construction of data that work with
построение они лишь данных работы с
this data
этими данными
allows us to make
позволяет как раз таки принимать
such decisions, give business advice, and
подобные решения давать советы бизнеса и
so on, all this naturally allows
так далее все это естественно позволяет
us to do technology, yes, it eats  if
нам делать технология да то есть если
traditional financial systems are based on
традиционные финансовые основаны на
some kind of legacy systems on traditional
каких-то legacy системах на традиционных
patience systems, then now
терпи системах то сейчас применяются и
aromatization is also used, even
ароматизация давай тоже даже а вчерашний
yesterday robotization is used when robots are used
день роботизация когда применяются
to
роботы для
release lists of routine steps
высвобождения про списках рутинных шагов
and locate people for more complex tasks,
и локации людей на более сложные задачи
not routine yes, this is the use of
не рутины да это применение
artificial intelligence  and machine
искусственного интеллекта и машинного
learning is just the same
обучения это как раз таки нужно для
for compiling effective models, this
для составления эффективных моделей это
is really ready, what a colleague
и действительно готова то чем коллега
said cryptocurrencies quantum
говорила криптовалюты квантовые
technologies, etc.
технологии так далее весь комплекс на
as for the process of
работе то что касается процесса
building the organizational structure of the
построения организационной структуры
financial function, if earlier in
финансовой функции если раньше в
traditional finance there were so
традиционных финансов существовали так
-called wells, now finance is
называемые колодцы то сейчас финансы
much closer business courts use
гораздо ближе бизнес суда используют
candle approaches when all
свеча подходы когда все
different departments work in one
разные подразделения работают в одной
common team in order to
общей команды для того чтобы быстрее
quickly  make decisions faster to give business
принимать решения быстрее давать бизнес
results, that’s all these
результат вот и то есть все эти
areas, in fact, yes, this is what
направления на самом деле да это то что
applicants should study in order to
должны абитуриенты изучая для того чтобы
have a full range of skills and yes,
обладать полным спектром а навыков да
in order to work in a modern
для того чтобы работать в современной
digital financial service, but probably
digital финансовой службе но наверное
like this, in short, a
вот так если коротко
great way to
прекрасный путь для наших студентов
it seems to me that for our students, take some square and
мне кажется вот бери какой-то квадрат и
then look at which next step you will go to,
потом смотри в какой следующий перейдешь
each step will be progress in work,
каждый шаг будет прогрессом в в работе в
work and career, I will
работе и карьере
add
добавлю
that most companies do this,
что большинство компаний этим занимаются
and in particular from 8 capital to which
да и в частности с 8 капитал до который
in any 0 and quite a lot
в любую 0 и достаточно много
invested  efforts in building
инвестировал усилий в построении
data warehouses in building all the
хранилищ данных в построении всех
tools so that you can
инструментов для того чтобы можно было
make informed decisions as well
принимать обоснованные решения так же
as all the key players in the market,
как и все ключевые игроки на рынке
so let's say where to apply this
поэтому ну скажем где применить эти
knowledge it is absolutely definitely
знания это абсолютно точно
there in this demand the need is what
есть на в этом спрос потребность это то
all the largest clients are working on
над чем работают все крупнейшие клиенты
in our market I will
на нашем рынке
perfectly cover a beautiful excellent
отлично прикрою прекрасная прекрасная
prospect for tr
перспектива по трудоустройству и
I want to give the floor to the representative of
я хочу передать слово представителю
investors to the
инвесторов
representative of the bank
представителю банка
if peter is with us peter I’m here yes how do you
если петр с нами петр я тут да как вас
manage to get out of
получается выйти
the black square of the black square for a
с черного квадрата черного квадрата до
long time yes now not black excellent
долгий да вот сейчас не черный отлично
petr dorozhkin representative of vtb bank a
петр дорожкин представитель банка втб
man with a
человек с
long and  productive careers within the
долгой и продуктивные карьеры и внутри
financial sector, but besides this
финансового сектора но помимо этого еще
, a person who
и человек который приходит
comes to the audience communicates with
приходит в аудиторию общается со
students
студентами
teaches at a Russian economic
преподает в российской экономической
school and
школе и
knows, knows
знает-знает
[music]
[музыка]
the needs of students, not
потребности потребностей студентов не
only in ours in ours but also in others in
только в наших в нашем но и в других в
other universities besides this  I asked
других вузах кроме этого я попросил
Peter to tell me, but
петра рассказать но а взгляде на
from the perspective of digitalization from the side of the investor and from the
цифровизация со стороны инвестора и со
side of the bank, and I again have the same question of
стороны банка и я опять тот же вопрос
how to learn this what is happening in the
как этому научиться что происходит
financial sector in terms of digitalization
финансовом секторе в части цифровизации
and the second question is how to learn
и второй вопрос как этому научиться
this thank you Eugene thank you for
такой спасибо евгений пасибо за
inviting me to this event,
приглашение на данное мероприятие
let me first  I will briefly introduce
давайте я сначала представлюсь кратко
myself  it would be clear what I'm going to talk about
чтобы было понятно о чем я буду говорить
my name is petr paths in the vtb group i am
меня зовут петр дорожки в группе втб я
responsible with long-term financial
отвечаю с долгосрочное финансовое
planning
планирование
for what western banks would call
за то что в западных банках назвали бы
finance strategies, that is, for the
стратегии финанс то есть за
formation of
формирование
long-term financial goals of the
долгосрочных финансовых целей
organization with this sight so that they
организации с этим прицелом чтобы они
justify the goals set by the
оправдывали те цели которые ставят
shareholders  which put the regulator
акционеры которые ставят регулятор
so on,
так далее
besides the fact that I work in finance, I
помимо того что я работаю финансах я
work in one of the most, let's
работающего на в одно из самых скажем
say, those intensive areas in the finger
так и те интенсивных сфер в фингер
divisions of the turkey
подразделений индейкой
before separation, which do not just work
до разделения которые не просто работает
with
с
friends in the digitalization of information technology more often,
друзьями в чаще пиза цифровизация за
namely,
информационной технологии а именно
probably with
наверное с
knowledge-intensive and part  lessons
наукоемкое и частью уроки представьте
imagine when it comes to planning a
себе когда речь идет о планировании
bank in any company then as a rule
банки в любой компании то как правило
highlights short-term planning
выделяет краткосрочное планирование
long-term planning
долгосрочное планирование
what you need we need a budget he can
что вам нужно нам нужен бюджет он может
business plan in this case usually
бизнес-план в этом случае как правило
people have food very process
люди имеет еду очень процессный
intensive very process intensive
интенсивный очень процессный интенсивный
process such a pun  then eats
процесс такая вот игра слов то есть
you just need to have
нужно просто чтобы
business partners, business or numbers in
бизнес-партнеры бизнес или циферки в
the stem system, everything neatly folded,
систему stem все аккуратно сложила
calculated, consolidated, we got the
посчитал консолидировала мы получили
result in my case, everything is more difficult
результат моем случае все сложнее
because you can take into account a lot of
поскольку можно учесть очень много
factors how the
факторов как будет развиваться экономика
economy will develop how the banking system will develop
как будет развиваться банковская система
how to maximize return on
как максимизировать доходность на
capital if necessary how to compare
капитал если это нужно как сопоставить
algorithms and techniques here down the bottom-up
алгоритмы и методики тут дауна bottom-up
which is used in forecasting
который используется в прогнозировании
this is the context of the visit what I
вот такое контекста визит о чем я
do of course I take interns every year
занимаюсь конечно же я каждый год беру
almost every
себе стажеров практически каждый ты
you replenish the team, that is,
происходит пополнение команда то есть
they have the opportunity to communicate with the hammer to the
они возможность общаться с молотка
young rising generation in
молодым подрастающим поколением в
view of this, I answer  questions who would
учитывая это я отвечаю на вопросы кто бы
build an answer as
построил построить ответ следующим
follows,
образом
saying digitalization, let's first
говоря цифровизации давайте сначала
think a little bit about the context that the
подумаем немножко контексте о том что
game is happening outside the window and
игра происходит за окном и
how we can act with what is happening outside the window as
как нам с тем что происходит за окном в
a whole, and what is happening outside the window is the
целом действовать а за окном происходит
following, I will be a little more
следующее я буду несколько более
specific, we have our own ball  So
конкретен у нас своя боль вот и
I’ll try, I’ll try, I’ll
попробую попробую
try, they’ll try to talk
попробую они поговорить
in the first place in the
во-первых
light of the events that are happening in our world
свете тех событий которую наш с мире
, companies are shortening the
происходят компании сокращают горизонт
planning horizon, that is, if earlier
планировать то есть если раньше больше
companies talked more about strategy about what
компании говорили о стратегии о том что
will happen in five years in 10-15
произойдет через пять лет через 10-15
now they are talking about what will happen
сейчас говорят о том что произойдет
next  year on the one hand to the truth
ближайший год с одной стороны до правда
on because the goal is to
на потому что цель час выжить как
survive this year how to live this year on the other hand, there is
прожить этот год в другой стороны все
still a great risk that we will lose the
таки велик риск того что мы потеряем
long-term goal and
долгосрочную цель и
having taken some actions during
произведя какие-то действия в течение
this year, having chosen the right path
этого года выбрав на правильную дорогу
or adjusting the minimum union,
или минимальный юния скорректировав не
we will not be able to adjust later  to speak on the right
сможем потом говорить на на нужную
trajectory, the
траекторию
first second trend that is now
первое второй тренд которые сейчас
present is, unfortunately, or parts of
присутствуют это к сожалению или части
import substitution,
импортозамещения
how is it what kind of impact does pineapple
как это какое влияние это ананас
have, we have certain
оказывает у нас есть определенные
software products west of them, these
программные продукты запад их эти законы
program laws, products must somehow not
программы продукты надо так или иначе не
just be replaced unfortunately, we are now
просто замещать сожалению мы сейчас
refusing situations when we  forced to
отказываемся ситуации когда мы вынуждены
maneuver between the functionality of convenient
лавировать между функционалом удобством
Western products and familiarity, let’s
западных продуктов и привычности скажем
say with the system implemented there and, let’s
так с реализованным там системы и скажем
say, certain features of
так определенными особенностями
domestic products that
отечественных продуктов которые
are still
до сих пор
not mature enough at some points,
некоторых моментах не достаточно зрелым
and of course, an important trend, an important detail, the
ну и конечно важный тренд важная деталь
context is the
контекст это бюджет
budget, given that it
с учетом того что
won’t be possible to earn much this year
заработать в этом году много не
at least  As far as banks have a
получится по крайней мере у банков
budget and cut
бюджет и режутся
that this is what, as a rule, customers
что это ч-что как правило заказчики
who allocate investor money they
которую выделяют деньги инвестора они
want
хотят
from those small investments that
из тех небольших инвестиций которые
cannot do anything from that porridge or
ничего не могут сделать из того каша или
from those activated their expenses
из тех активизирован их расходов
to get the maximum, unfortunately, the cost of
получить максимум к сожалению расходы на
automation is not digitalization of the financial
автоматизацию не цифровизация финансово
department here  can hardly be attributed
департамента сюда вряд ли можно отнести
because they have a long horizon a
поскольку они имеют длинный горизонта
long payback horizon
длинный горизонт окупаемости
what follows from this context what
что вытекает из этого контекста какие
difficulties they have what trends we have in the framework of the
сложности их какие тренды у нас в рамках
digitalization of the financial function at
цифровизации финансовой функции крайней
least I do not see the
мере я сопла коль не вижу
number one difficulty
сложность номер один
planning how long-term it is
планирование как долгосрочно это
short-term activision with  working with
краткосрочная activision при работе с
colleagues it becomes more complicated
коллегами она становится более сложная
before we had conditionally 5 counterparties
раньше у нас было условно 5 контрагентов
now we have about ten counterparties
теперь у нас порядка десяти контрагентов
everyone wants their own cut everyone wants
каждый хочет свой разрез каждый хочет
their own word of this model the
свою слове данной модели
number of outs that this model
количество аутов которые у этой модели
has it also grows that is earlier if
есть она тоже растет то есть раньше если
you set all the strategic goals you
вы ставили все стратегические цели вы
wanted all the implementation of the detailing just a
хотели все реализацию детализация просто
multiplier on the target profit for
мультипликатор на целевую прибыль по
now you need June because  but Mecca and
теперь нужно июня т.к. но мекку и
some of the g parameters of their scenario magician,
какие-то из g параметры их мага
that is, calculate for us and for several
то есть посчитайте нам и для нескольких
options what will happen if and to be
вариантов а что будет если а чтобы быть
if and what will happen if this all
если а что будет если это все
imposes certain
накладывает определенные
requirements since childhood on
требования пор не так детстве на
those software products those requirements for
те программные продукты те требования к
civilization that  which we share, of
цивилизации которые которые мы разделяем
course, of course, they are naturally complicated by the
конечно конечно их усложняет
financial director, he
естественно финансовый директор он
significantly develops, the
существенно развивается увеличиваются
functionality increases, he moves absolutely
функционалу передвигает абсолютно
correctly yes, that is, earlier on top of the
правильно да то есть раньше сверху от
account, now it is also himself and the
аккаунтом теперь это еще и себя и
main person for information
главный человек за информационной
security,
безопасности
which is not what it means that
чего только нет что это значит что
when more is added within the financial department
когда в рамках финансовых департамента
one digital product, it is
добавляется еще один цифровой продукт он
forced to integrate with a much
вынужден интегрироваться с гораздо
larger number of systems
большим числом систем
and
и
this leads to an increase in financial costs,
это ведет к росту затрат как
and you are just a single person and
финансовых а ты просто человек одни и
increases the risk of errors
увеличивает риск ошибок
with this very integration, which
при вот этой вот самой интеграции что
is important the very previous paragraph about the fact that
важно само предыдущий пункт про то что
now it is very difficult to prove that
сейчас очень тяжело доказать про то что
investments  at the pace they are somehow  - something at least
инвестиции в темпе они хоть как-то хоть
somehow extremely
как-то предельно
well, in general, I would say that there is the
ну и в целом я бы сказал что существует
following problem
следующая проблема
now within the country and within
сейчас в рамках страны и в рамках
business very much attention to the
бизнеса очень большое внимание к
field of information technology they say
сфере информационных технологий говорят
that predators 2 oil is probably true
что хищники 2 нефть наверное это правда
but let's not forget about what
но давайте не будем забывать про то что
to go  the bed itself, it cannot work
идти сама постели она не может работать
without a customer, and here, between the
без заказчика и вот здесь вот между
customer, us as a customer and as
заказчиком нами как заказчиком и д как
performers, there is a certain
исполнителям существует некоторый
vector and a gap, these are people who,
вектор и пробел это люди которые должны
on the one hand, need to know the financial aspects of the
с одной стороны знать финансовые аспекты
other side, know the IT aspects
другой стороны знать айтишные аспекты
, unfortunately, in this area now there are
к сожалению вот в этой сфере сейчас есть
certain  lack of personnel,
определенные недостаток кадров
partly these personnel left, partial these
частично эти кадры уехали частичные эти
personnel were for the rights of men and were promoted and,
кадры были за права мужчин и повышены и
let's say, they may not be completely
скажем так может быть не совсем
managed with work as well as we
управляются так хорошо с работой как это
would like, and here there is a
хотелось бы и вот здесь вот есть
potential for those students
потенциал для того чтобы те студенты
who are graduating tomorrow into this niche to
которые завтра выпускается в эту нишу
fill
заполнили
that  such students need to
что таким студентам нужно
know so that they can take their
знать для того чтобы они могли занять их
course successfully about social security.
мишу успешно про собеседованиями темы
well, first of all, as I said,
работы ну во первых как я сказал
understanding both financial somehow and
понимание как финансовых как-то так и
technical aspects of the principle of
технических аспектов принципе работы
work, where,
работать где по
secondly, this is probably a
второе это наверное
good mathematical base, whatever one may say
хорошая математическая база как ни крути
, I have a first technical education and
у меня первое образование техническое и
within the framework of
в рамках
one of the projects that we did, we
одного из проектов который мы делали мы
did not  more less a multidimensional
делали не больше меньше многомерном
financial model
финансовую модель
is such a step forward over excel when
это такой step forward над экселем когда
you apply a model of a two-dimensional
вы модель прикладываетесь двумерной
table in
таблица в многомерно
multidimensionally, this base is very necessary in order
вот эта база она очень нужна для того
to put a tz-type recession base under the
чтобы подложить базе спада тип tz под те
tasks that we set as downloads and
задачи которые мы как закачки ставим и
which predators must
которая техники хищники должны должны
understand,
понять
you need to understand  the basics of the operation of
необходимо понимать основы работы
algorithms, for example,
алгоритмов например
such an example of a dilemma in france
такими пример дилеммы во франции
modeling is separable complexity times
моделирования отделимо сложность раз
transparency
прозрачность и
and from a practical point of view, of course
их с практической точки зрения конечно
, more practice is needed, that is,
нужно больше практики то есть
conditionally more people from faster who
условно больше людей из быстрее которые
speak at least like me as speakers in the
выступают хотя бы как я спикеры на
classroom in order for students to have
занятиях для того чтобы у студентов
siding, they have such  let's
появился сайдинг появился них такое вот
say  m of what is happening here now,
скажем того что происходит здесь сейчас
but not in the classroom, but in the office
но не в аудитории а в офисе
what tasks are set by customers like
какие задачи ставятся заказчиками как
these customers pain what tasks they
этих заказчиков боль какие задачи они
set how they are implemented
ставят как они реализуются
we of course probably have more practice with
мы конечно наверное больше практики с
all sorts of different computational tasks
всякими разными вычислительными задачами
mathematical
математическому
I would say the level is much higher than we
я бы сказал уровня сильно выше чем мы
goals 11 here  that is, if we look
цели 11 вот то есть то если мы смотрим
there also a trainee in ourselves that, let's say, in the
там также стажера в себе ту скажем так в
movies, they even amg things to the ball, yes, that
кино лаки они даже amg вещи на бал да то
is, we don’t even ask people, we
есть мы даже не спрашиваем людей мы
think that we can stand it very well,
считаем что выдержу очень хорошо владеет
be able to program, so, if
уметь программировать вот наверное если
briefly, then the
кратко то
answer to the question is still
ответа на вопрос таки
Peter  thank you very much for such a
петр большое спасибо за такой
comprehensive view and
всеобъемлющей взгляд и
valuable ideas, to
ценные идеи
be honest, it’s a little sobering that the
если честно немножко так отрезвляет что
financial department is low on financial initiatives,
рое от финансовых инициатив финансовый
and that these
департамент и низкий и что вот эти
initiatives are actually low
инициативы на самом деле низко
margin, long payback,
маржинальные долго окупаемые
it’s low, I may be a little
он низкий я немножко может быть
wrong said very hard to prove
неправильно сказал очень тяжело доказать
that this is really old  high just
что это старый действительно высокий вот
imagine that in order to
представьте себе что для того чтобы
highlight the day  gi in reality you need
выделили деньги в реальности вам нужно
to go through three or four committees and in
пройти три или четыре комитета и в
each of these committees you need to
каждом из этих комитетов нужно
provide something and
предоставлять то и
they called it to represent
назвали представлять у
everyone in different ways but how do we
всех по разному да как вот у нас там
do a lot for one thing your big
за один делаю очень много ваша большая
competition
конкуренция
here you have roughly the boundaries of otiev
вот у вас есть грубо границы отиева
business which  clear to schools and
бизнеса у которой четкий к школ и
clearly the shield of the world, and here you come
четко щит мира и и тут вы приходите
to tell him how it would be, let's
говорить ему как бы это вот давайте
automate planning how much it will
автоматизирует планирование сколько это
save people, on the contrary, there
сэкономит людей несколько наоборот надо
will be more people
будет больше людей
how much
сколько
money you can save on this, yes, on the
сможете сэкономить на этом денег ну да
contrary,
несколько наоборот потребуются
investment in software products will be
инвестиции в программных продуктов
required, and in what  then it makes sense
доработку а в чем тогда смысл
to do it anyway, it’s necessary to do it equally,
делать все равно надо делать с равно
yes, but we’ll kind of get away from the
надо да но мы как бы уйдем от каменного
taxil’s stone ax and move on to some kind of
топора таксиля да и перейдём в какую-то
industrial system, we’ll reach the
промышленную систему выйдем на на
world level, excellent, what’s the
мировой уровень отлично какой от этого
point of proving that
толк приходится доказывать что
three bag-ends are of course complex, such as
трое бэг-энда конечно сложный такой как
once and I want to say that what is possible
раз и хочу сказать что то что что можно
not for when knowing how hard it is
не для когда зная как это проходит
in large companies and  how many times
тяжело в больших компаниях и сколько раз
do you need
нужно
to lay your head down so that you cut it off,
положить голову чтобы тебе ее отрубили
it’s better not to stick it there right away, but I’m
лучше сразу ее не совать туда но я
because these committees, yes, of
потому что вот эти комитета да они
course, they are hard to explain
конечно тяжело объясняемые
Peter, you can also have a question
петр можно еще вот вопрос
about a swarm from an intern and
про роя от стажёра и
here are young employees through at what
вот молодых сотрудников через в какой
point in time or through what tests
момент времени или через какие испытания
or  what kind of transformation of a young
или какую трансформацию вот молодого
employee this return from a new
сотрудника этот отдача от нового
specialist becomes positive what
специалиста становится положительной что
should happen, it’s just the passage of
должно произойти просто это течение
time or some kind of
времени или какие-то вы выделяете
significant events
знаковые события
when a specialist becomes useful and
когда специалист становится полезным и
brings added value
приносит добавленную стоимость
positive
положительную
good question I would say one of the
хороший вопрос я бы сказал один из
important stages when a person can become a
важных этапов когда человек может рабом
slave  one of the important stages comes that
один из важных этапов наступает тот
person gets the opportunity to work
человек получает возможность работать
independently
самостоятельно
does not distract my time and the time of the mars of
не отвлекает мое время и время марс
experienced people,
учиненных опытных людей уже
let's say it happens for myself, it happens
скажем так на себя происходит по это
in different ways,
по-разному
I would say that probably a person goes
я бы сказал что наверное человек выходит
to independent work tramer in a
на самостоятельную работу трамер через
year is
год
excellent,
отлично
in general, two years in  master's degree and one
в общем два года в магистратуре и один
from these years should already begin with
из этих годов уже должен начинаться
practice so that already at the exit from the
практикой чтобы уже на выходе из
magistracy to give a positive effect
магистратуры дать положительный эффект
for the employer to a
для работодателя
good before after the first entry of the
хорошему до после первого ввода
magistracy, the exit for an internship and,
магистратура выход на стажировку и
accordingly, with a diploma, a person can already
соответственно с дипломом человек уже
get a promotion to become a
вполне может получить промоушена стать
full-fledged
полноценным
employee with a poor experience and are ready to
сотрудникам нищим опыт и готовы
replenish
пополнению
it, thank you very much for your  the comment
это большое спасибо за ваш комментарий
for us is very valuable for us to
для нас для нас очень ценно для
build a training plan for our
построения плана подготовки наших
students,
студентов
I want to give the floor to oleg
хочу передать передать слово олегу
nazarov, who also joined our
назарову которую же включился в нашу
discussion oleg is
дискуссию олег
a financial market professional with a
профессионал финансового рынка с
proven work history worked
доказанной истории работы на нем работал
in a management company
в управляющей компании альянс альянс
the other part of the
настоящее время работает в другой части
spectrum of
спектра
companies is an entrepreneur and
компаний является предпринимателем и
founder of a start-up in the field of fitness and fitness
основателем стартапа в области и фитнес
industry Oleg,
индустрии олег вот
taking into account such a broad outlook, how
с учетом такого широкого кругозора как
do you see the digitalization of finance among
тебе видится цифровизация финансов у
big players and perhaps not so
больших игроков и у возможно не таких
big ones and what should students do  Thanks
больших и что делать студентам спасибо
to the entam, in fact,
на самом деле
somehow returning to past experience, I can
как то возвращаясь к прошлому опыту могу
say, well, it’s clear that listening to everything that is
сказать ну понятно что слушая все что
being condemned here today, it’s clear that the
сегодня здесь осуждается понятно что
financial function of seafight is a very
финансовой функции seafight очень
conservative function and and and role, and
консервативная функция и и и и роль и
therefore, as Irina said, as if in
поэтому как ирина сказала как бы в
large companies, there is a gulf between
крупных компаниях пропасть между
traditional finance and  where it’s
традиционными финансами и туда куда это
all important to come sometime she’s big with
все важно когда-то прийти она большая с
this I completely agree that
этим полностью согласен могу сказать что
on the other side in extremes in small
на другой край в крайности в малом
business
бизнесе
digital finance or numbers and sculpted the
цифровые финансы или цифрам и лепили
digital function of finance is a daily
цифровая функция финансов это ежедневная
necessity this is something without which, in principle, it is
необходимость это то без чего в принципе
almost impossible to live firstly because
почти невозможно жить во первых потому
that small companies small businesses
что у малых компаний малого бизнес
simply do not have the money to hire
просто нет денег для того чтобы нанять
from above
сверху
more often all the functions of the safe are connected
чаще все функции сейфа соединяется
within one person the functions are related to the
внутри одного человека функции связаны с
business associated with attracting
бизнесом связанные с привлечением
investments the spread associated with advertising
инвестиций спред связанный с с рекламой
with sales with the product and
с продажами с продуктом и
it is forced to connect here
она вынужденным образом соединяется вот
with one from one end  with what
с одном с одного конца с того что
is called accounting and cou  nting
называется бухгалтерский учет и counting
management accounting financial
управленческий учет финансовое
planning and so on with what
планирование и так далее с тем ну что
is at the other end i.e. with the
находится на другом конце то есть с
result with sales with revenue with
результатом с продажами с выручкой со
all this in this sense
всем этим в этом смысле
they are not separated they are in the same
они не разделены они находятся в одной
head at the extreme in two if there are
голове крайним случаем в двух если есть
two partners or in 3 if  there is also a
два партнера или в 3 если есть и
partner for most often a
партнера на чаще всего
financial director or the function of a
финансовый директор или функции
financial director in a small business, a
финансового директора в малом бизнесе
function that is very close to the
функция которая очень близка к
financial result in terms of revenue or
финансовому результат к выручке или к
profit or sales, and
прибыли или к продажам и
in order for it to work, you first
для того чтобы это заработало во первых
need to buy it if possible or
нужно по возможности купить или там
outsource it or install it
аутсорсить или там установить себе
yourself  -solutions that will help
какие-то решения которые помогут
to replace traditional financial functions in some way without spending too
образом заменить не тратя на не слишком
much time, therefore, relatively speaking,
много времени поэтому условно говоря
now there are most banks for the
сейчас там большинстве банка для
self-employed there is always the opportunity to
самозанятых всегда есть возможность
calculate their taxes to pay them don’t
рассчитать свои налоги уплатить их не
do it with your own hands
делай это своими собственными руками
, I can also say that by my own
тоже могу сказать что на собственном
example
примере
if finances if if person in
если финансы если если человек
charge of finance  Ansy does not see how
отвечающий за финансы не видит как
revenue is generated based on the results of
формируется выручка по результатам
an advertising campaign does not understand how
рекламной кампании не понимает каким
the
образом
company receives
вообще на счета компании поступают
money
деньги
at all as a result of expenses spent on advertising
в результате потраченных на рекламу
, well, this most often does not
расходов ну то это чаще всего не
work now it can be done now
работает сейчас это можно сделать сейчас
all advertising is most of the advertising
вся реклама это большая часть рекламы
is advertising in social networks and
это реклама в социальных сетях и
this advertisement is a shield abundantly and when I, as a
эта реклама щит обильно и когда я как
financial director, call my
финансовый директор назовем своей
company, I
компании
discuss with the guys what kind of advertisement
обсуждаю с ребятами какую рекламу
to launch, then I look at advertisements not as
запускать то я смотрю на рекламы не как
no cost that we have to spend and
no cost который мы должны потратить и
then maybe we will get something, but as a
потом может быть что-то получим а как на
set of parameters that will lead to a
набор параметров который приведет к
certain result
определенному результату
they do it only due to the fact that all these
делают только благодаря тому что все эти
numbers, all these parameters, all these even
цифры все эти параметры все эти даже
boards, we have the presence in this sense,
борды у нас есть наличие в этом смысле у
we don’t have any legacy as a small business
нас нет ни как у малого бизнеса нету
and
никакого legacy и
it lives as if cutting corners as much as possible,
он живет как бы максимально срезая углы
Peter said that
пётр сказал о том что
you need to go through several layouts  to
нужно пройти несколько макетов чтобы
convince people that what is needed is something to
убедить людей в том что что нужно что то
endorse the figure
цифра визировать
so it is clear that in small  in business there is no
так понятно что в малом бизнесе нет
time for a committee there is no time
времени на комитета нету времени на то
to
чтобы
change the legacy simply because of these
менять legacy просто потому что этих
stereotypes and the capable type, I mean
стереотипов и способна тип имею ввиду
just the usual pre-revolutionary
просто привычные предреволюционные
methods for solving
методы решения
financial problems, they are simply not there, you just need to do
финансовых задач их просто не туда нужно
it here and now in some
просто здесь и сейчас каким-то образом
way to
делать так чтобы
spend money on
тратить деньги на
sales, we  we knew exactly how much we would get from them
продаже мы знали точно сколько мы от них
and for this we use all the
получим и для этого мы используем все
possibilities that exist on the market
возможности которые существуют на рынке
we we use stripe as a
мы мы мы используем stripe как систему
budgeting system for financial
бюджетирования систем финансового
planning systems I simplify this on
планирования я это упрощая специально
purpose, however I use we
дано тем не менее я использую мы
use all kinds of
используем всевозможные
connect and to
connect и к
programs sold there that
продажным там программам который
allows  we immediately understand after we
позволяет нам тут же понимать по
spent this money and we will most
потратили этих денег и получим скорее
likely get y
всего y
than to do it in real time and
чем это делать в реальном времени и
understanding, as it were, that every dollar spent by
понимая ну как бы что каждый потраченный
a yuan football player will lead to
доллар футболистом юань приведет
some kind of revenue
какой-то выручки
in a day, two days later,
через день через два дня
you can ask alik well, and some so to
алика можно спросить ну и какой то так
say that  in small companies, then such
сказать что в малых компаниях то таких
startups are very dynamic  a temporary
стартапах очень динамичных современных
financial function, it partially
финансовая функция она частично
dissolves in other functions, I can
растворяется в других функциях я могу
say that, yes, venture companies in
сказать что да что венчурных компаний в
startups, small businesses,
стартапах малом бизнесе
financial functions, the financial director
финансовой функции финансовый директор
as a function cannot afford to
как функция не может себе позволить ни
be as close as possible to the business, so
быть максимально близким бизнесу вот
network developers can afford not to
сетевом может себе позволить не
understand finance, on the
разбираться финанс
contrary, for years, but on the contrary, no  well, simply
наоборот лет а наоборот нет ну просто
because then nothing will happen and
потому что тогда ничего не произойдет и
in this sense, how if you answer
в этом смысле как вот если отвечать на
question 2 that you have is that
вопрос 2 который у тебя стоит это что
how to learn all this I can say
как этому всему научиться я могу сказать
my own experience I have never been a
мой собственный опыт я никогда не был
siphon I worked a lot for sifu of
сифону я очень много работал сифу
large companies but when I  became an
больших компаний но когда я стал
entrepreneur, then I realized that in order
предпринимателем то я понял что для того
to be able to connect
чтобы иметь возможность соединять
the financial function with business and
функцию финансовую с бизнесом и
there with development, because development
там с разработкой потому что разработка
is
является
an integral part of the whole picture,
неотъемлемой частью всей картины
you need to be a product manager, so
нужно быть продакт-менеджер по этому как
as you and I discussed,
мы с тобой обсуждали
this is what would be nice, let's
вот то что было бы неплохо давайте
teach students this  product
студентам это обучать продакт
management which connects  as a
менеджменту которая соединяет в себе
matter of fact IT business and finance
собственно говоря айти бизнес и финансы
you may not be an expert enter
ты можешь не быть специалистом войти
such as this developer
таким как является эти разработчик ты
you may not be an expert in
можешь не быть специалистом в
business in marketing the one who
бизнесе в маркетинге таким который
is an advertising specialist
является специалистом по рекламе ты
you may not even be a very deep
можешь даже не быть слишком глубоким
specialist in accounting
специалистом по бухгалтерскому учету
someone must understand  all this
кто-то должен разбираться во всем этом
in order to be able to
для того чтобы иметь возможность это
combine this on the first of May to own the work
соединить это первое мая владеть работу
and release the product in order to give the
и выпустить продукт для того чтобы дать
product so that it enters the
продукт для того чтобы он вышел на рынок
market so that you start buying
для того чтобы вы начали покупать для
so that it's all somewhere 2 gross and the
того чтобы это все куда-то 2 gross и
second moment is important too  that the
второй момент важны тоже что
financial director or there the financial
финансовый директор или там финансовая
function should get used to taking
функция должна привыкнуть принимать
risks I started by saying that she is very
риска я начал с того что она очень
conservative initially the traditional
консервативно изначально традиционный
financial director herself is a conservative
финансовый директор самой консерванта
what this
что пытается избежать вот эта серия
series of commissions and committees is
каскад из из комиссий и комитетов они
trying to avoid they are trying to avoid risk yes but we are now
пытаются избежать риска да но мы сейчас
talking about how to teach  people who
говоря о том как учить людей которые
must at this moment
должны в это момент
adapt this system  the topic to turn
адаптировать эту систему до превратить
it into a more mobile pain figure drawn
ее более подвижной боли цифра рисованные
they must learn to take risks
они должны научиться принимать риски
because well, as if business is always
потому что ну как бы бизнес это всегда
an attempt to get somewhere, it can
попытка куда то выйти она может
end in failure and for any
закончиться неудачей и для любого
traditional CFO
традиционного финансового директора
any failure is a loss that needs to be
любая неудача это убыток которые нужно
written off that needs to be explained to the
списывать свои который нужно объяснять
committee and shareholders  and so on and
комитетом и акционерам и так далее а
if you are a digital financial director you
если ты цифровой финансовый директор ты
just understand that this is an inevitable
просто понимаешь что это неизбежная
part of life here now it is to be blamed
часть жизни здесь сейчас это надо винить
to accept this is a very complicated story this is an
принимать это очень сложная история это
old man Andreeva's appearance equals
старик appearance андреевой равно
venture turns out to be autocad in fact this is
венчурные получается autocad по сути это
exactly how this story
именно так это история который
begins with if I'm sorry if
начинается с если прошу прощения если
if  I’m over forty, it’s very difficult to learn to understand
если мне за сорок то научиться понимать
risks, because I was taught
риски очень тяжело потому что меня учили
all the way how to avoid them
всю дорогу как бы их избегать их
, but if you’re 20, then there’s still
избегать вот но если тебе 20 то это еще
a great chance to learn this, well, this
есть большой шанс научиться этому ну это
subject can be called whatever you like given
предмет как угодно можно называть дано
this entrepreneurship in fact yes, a very
это предпринимательства по сути да очень
important component  for us too much
важная составляющая для нас тоже много
visible  that is, at the undergraduate level, and by the way, the
видимые на уровне бакалавриата и кстати
propensity for risk and entrepreneurship
склонность к риску и предпринимательству
in management programs, for example, and in
на программах менеджмента например и на
economics programs, these economics programs
программах экономики данным программах
are attended by more people with an
экономики идут больше люди с
analytical warehouse and tend to
аналитическим складом и и склонны
work in such a more secure
работать вот в такой более защищенной
environment, such regulated large
среде такой регламентированные крупных
companies and those who go to management to
компаний и те кто идут на менеджмент к
those  who want to go on
те кто хотят пойти на
but create their own business to go into
но создать свой бизнес пойти
entrepreneurship and we, as a university, as a
предпринимательства и мы как вуз как
university, want to give people the opportunity
университет хотим дать возможность
to develop, and with those and other
развиваться и людям и с теми и с другими
preferences,
предпочтениями людям а
and
и
most importantly, that they find each other and
главное чтобы они нашли друг друга и
know how to work with each other, I think
умели друг с другом работать мне кажется
it was for us  would be a very good
для нас это была бы очень хорошим
result for us and for our
результатом для нас и для наших
students,
студентов
thank you very much
спасибо большое
for wanting to just add the last drop
что хотел такого просто последнюю каплю
to these subjects that would be
добавить к этим предметам который был бы
properly studied not a subject, probably,
правильно изучать не предметом наверное
but you just need to just show more
а просто нужно просто показывать больше
business cases, you need
бизнес кейсов нужно
to go beyond large companies in
выходить за рамки больших компаний для
order to broaden your horizons a little
того чтобы немножко расширить кругозор
because only that  well, it
потому что только там ну начинается то
starts with the beginning of the very digitalization that
начинается та самая цифровизация который
big companies will think in their mouths for a long time
большие компании будут еще долго думать
simply because it’s a big legacy and
в рот просто потому что большой legacy и
needs to be changed a lot,
нужно много менять
yes, but maybe a big legacy can
ну да но возможно большой legacy может
be a big buyer for a small
быть большим покупателем для небольшого
startup with a big assessment, but not now,
стартапа с большой оценкой да не сейчас
really, due to different circumstances  but in the
правда силу разных обстоятельств но в
future, but once thanks, big oleg
будущем но когда-то спасибо большой олег
wanted to give the floor to alexey kalashnikov
хотел передать слово алексей калашников
alexey you are with us
алексей вы с нами
good evening colleagues
добрый вечер коллеги
alexey the current financial director
алексей действующий финансовый директор
finally we got to how to say
наконец-то мы дошли до как сказать
really a person from the industry a
действительно человека из отрасли
person because of the difficult industry and for
человека из-за непростой отрасли и за
close friendly geography alexey
близкое дружественные география алексей
works for the multi-profile holding
работает по многопрофильному холдинге
orient uzbekistan and is developing the
orient узбекистан и занимается развитием
development of different segments of this
развитием разных сегментов этого этого
business alexey how can you make sure the
бизнеса алексей как тебе убедиться
digitalization of the financial function
цифровизация финансовой функции
socialization doesn’t happen not only in
социализация она не бывает не только в
russia, it happens in their countries next to
россии она бывает их странах рядом с
russia, oddly enough,
россией как как как ни странно
socialization is such a buzzword now,
социализации сейчас такое модное слово
although it seems to me that this is one of the
хотя мне кажется что это один из из
tools, although speaking about numbers, the
инструментах хотя говоря про цифры
task makes sense separates
задачу имеет смысл разделяет
traditional and digital business now
традиционный и цифровой бизнес сейчас
there are many
появилось много
businesses that initially build themselves
бизнесов которые изначально себя строит
as digital, that is, there are all processes
как цифровые то есть там все процессы
processes related to business, rather,
процессы связанные с бизнесом скорее то
years have passed, they have already been digitized,
прошло говорила лет они уже оцифрованы
yes, that is, there is a figure, he and sales are
да то есть там цифра он и продажи там
digitized there, purchases are digitized there, the
оцифрованы закупки там оцифрована
value chain is digitized and
цепочка со за создание стоимостей и
therefore the digitalization of processes it
поэтому цифровизация процессов она за
entails  it is necessary to digitize the
собой влечет обязательно цифровизация
accounting of accounting functions and all the
учета учетных функций и всего того
functionality
функционала
that you own, you must
которым владеет обладает ты обязан
own the financial director, that is, this
владеть финансово директор то есть этой
accounting and reporting planning and
учета и отчетности планирования и
budgeting and controlling, and there
бюджетирования и контроллинг и там
investment projects,
инвестиционные проекты
that is, in digital in digital business,
то есть в цифровом в цифровом бизнесе
without digitalization, there is no longer anywhere the
без а цифровизации уже не уже некуда
process is already digitized  If we
процесс итак итак оцифрованы если мы
we go aside in the traditional business of
идем в сторону в традиционного бизнеса
tons, then it’s probably worth saying first of
тонн то наверное стоит говорить в первую
all that the
очередь что
basis is important for the financial director, that is, for dad, firstly, the business
базис то есть папе во-первых бизнес сам
itself should already be quite
сам по себе должен быть уже достаточно
mature, the
зрелой
business process should be established
должны должны устояться бизнесовые
again, the same
процесс опять тех же самых там
production, purchases, sales  from the point of
производства закупок продаж с точки
view of finance
зрения финансов должен быть создан
, a certain minimum should be created, that is, the
создан некий некий минимум то есть
company should already be able to
компания уже и так и так должна уметь
take into account planning budgeting,
учитывать планировать бюджетирование
calculate
ровать просчитывать свои сайтами
investment projects with its websites, and here, probably,
инвестиционные проекты и вот наверное на
at the junction of a
нас на стыке
working business and a financially minimally
работающего бизнеса и минимально
created
созданного
direction of the
финансово финансово направления
financial block, a headlight appears  zation
финансового блока появляется фа ре зация
as another tool, again
как еще один инструмент опять же про
speaking about centralization, digitalization can be distinguished
говоря про централизацию можно выделить
as such an expanded
цифровизация как расширенную такую
accounting system, that is, the ability to
учетную систему то есть возможность
quickly
быстро
receive information ayodhya to store and and
получать информацию айодхьи хранить и и
will be considered from different angles, and
рассматривать будут под разными углами и
then this is the first part and the second part is
то это первая часть а вторая часть это
still a civilization process  with that is,
все-таки цивилизация процесс то есть
digitalization of coordination digitalization of
цифровизация согласования цифровизация
budgeting digitalization of controlling,
бюджетирования цифровизация контроллинга
that is, those same traditional basic
то есть тех самых традиционных базовых
basic functions that will
базовых функций накано который будет
take a lot of time, but still
уходит много много времени но и все таки
on which reporting such improved
на котором и reporting такой улучшенный
reporting is faster more accurate
reporting более быстрые более точные
more segmented yes and the second is
более сегментированные да а второе это
some also yes  yes definitely
какие-то также да да безусловно а также
and also more transparent
а также более более прозрачный более
more understandable cheaper and more
более понятный более дешевый и более
convenient because if I put one digit
удобные потому что если я одну цифру
into the system once and I can copy the
один раз положил в систему и я могу copy
digit from different angles and
цифре обращаться под разными углами а
can I put in one reporting form in
могу я положить в одну форм отчетности в
another I can
другую я могу
assume  that it will grow two times
предположить что она вырастет два раза
or three times that it will
или в три раза что она что оно
shrink elites and speech and or something else, well,
сократится элит и речь и или еще что ну
that is, that is, I should not, firstly
то есть то есть я не должен во первых
, the same data if we
одни и те же и те же данные если мы
are talking about digitalization as an accounting
говорим про цифровизация как учетную
system, I am not India  should transfer the same
систему я индия не должен одни и те же
data from different systems to
данные перекидывать из разных систем в
different ones there, produce errors, and secondly, I
разные там плоди ошибки а во-вторых я
can, I can transparently for myself  I am both for and
могу я могу прозрачно для себя и для и
for a circle earlier for investors for a hand
для кружа раньше для инвесторов для рука
for guidance for colleagues from the right
для руководства для коллег из правильных
departments I can show that we are like we are
отделов я могу показывать что мы как мы
where we are, well, that is, all the company’s activities are still
где мы ну то есть все таки
permeated with money
деньгами пронизана вся деятельность
, so what I often say to
компании поэтому че я часто говорю к
colleagues and caused in general despite
коллегам и причиненным общем несмотря на
our  wonderful wonderful missions
наши прекрасные замечательной миссии
that are especially loved by big companies
которые любят особенно больших компаниях
we are here to make
мы здесь собрались чтобы деньги
money we are not here to
зарабатывать мы не для того чтобы
produce equipment saying I don’t know
производить оборудование говоря не знаю
machines clothes or food
машинами одеждой или продуктами питания
we are here to earn money so
мы здесь деньги зарабатывать поэтому
let’s measure all our wonderful
давайте все наши замечательные
initiatives in terms
инициативы будем мерить относительно
of how they help to make
того как они помогают зарабатывать
money and how  since
деньги и как раз
digitalization is a tool in my opinion,
инструмент цифровизация на мой взгляд и
and this is an important task of the
и это является важной задачей
financial director, it is still
финансового директора это все-таки
helping to make money, it is possible for you
помогать зарабатывать деньги у вас
to use efforts to
возможно применение усилий
relocate capital to some other
релокации капитала в какое-то другое
direction will bring much
направление принесет гораздо гораздо
more returns now it is necessary at this
больше отдачу сейчас надо на данном
stage of life data in this company
этапе жизни данные в данной компании
can  we don’t know if we should train
может быть нам не знаешь стоит обучать
staff or hire staff,
персонал или нанимать персонал может
maybe we should modify our
быть нам стоит модифицирует наше
equipment, or maybe we should
оборудование а может быть нам стоит
start digitalization of processes
запускается цифровизация процессов
because we will gain something from this something to
потому что мы от этого что-то что-то
gain time accuracy
выиграть время точность сокращение
cost reduction market market
сокращение расходов рыночную рыночную
value because investors like
стоимость потому что инвесторы любит
words words digitalization and the introduction of a
слова слова цифровизация и внедрение
large beautiful dress and product
большого красивого одевать и продукта
increases the market value of the company
повышает рыночную стоимость компании к
new new investors come to us we
нам приходят новые новые инвесторы мы мы
show our beautiful transparent
показываем наш прекрасный прозрачный
business that we see from any
бизнес который мы видим под любыми
angle you want as you like so
углами хотите по хотите так хотите так
we will cut it to you my city and see the business
мы вам мой город его разрежем и бизнес
and it  we are managing it, therefore
видим и его мы его управляя поэтому
, after all, digitalization, in my opinion, this
все-таки цифровизация на мой взгляд это
is a tool, in my opinion,
это инструмент на мой взгляд
digitalization makes sense to deal with
цифровизации имеет смысл заниматься
when the business is mature enough, when in
когда бизнес достаточно зрелой когда в
general
целом
there is an understanding from the model,
есть пониманием от модели
there are basic
есть базовые
basic functions, the functionality of the
базовые функции функционал уже
financial department already and
финансового отдела и
we should deal with the implementation to give birth
мы должны заниматься реализацией родить
for the sake of something
ради чего-то
probably this  under the soup of civilization, yes, but
наверное это под супа цивилизации да но
alexey to spin a real phone
алексей наткать настоящий телефон
that you can’t say that everything
который не можете сказать что все
happens
происходит
for the sake of the financial result and the
ради-ради финансового результата и
value of the company, thank you very much
стоимости компании большое спасибо
look,
взгляд а
but about the students that he was also a
по поводу студентов что он тоже был был
question, I would like to
вопрос мне бы хотелось
see that
видеть понимать что студент приходящий
he already has a student coming from the university  there is some
из университета у него уже есть некая на
visibility I don’t know how
смотре ность не знаю как как это
to choose words correctly in Russian these
правильно по русски подобрать слова это
are the same cases the same tools
вот те самые кейсы те самые инструменты
as applied to different red companies
в применении к разным красном компании
that what you see happens like this we can
что что смотрите бывает вот так мы можем
take
взять не знаю на коленке ли стопка
something
листов бумаги и у нас во что-то что-то
works, maybe this is how we
работает а может быть вот так мы вот
apply this tool here and with
этот инструмент прикладываем сюда и у
us and with us it should also be
нас и у нас он должен тоже приносит
beneficial, but it happens like this is a disk
пользу пользу а бывает вот так диск где
where there is no financial department
где сифоне это финансового отдела нету
but everything but everyone is imbued with ideas of
но все но все проникнуты идеи
making money  but it happens somehow
зарабатывания денег а бывает еще как-то
1 then, of course, you want at least
1 потом конечно же хочется хотя бы
basic
базовых навыков
programming skills, not even for a
программирования даже не для того чтобы
person to come and with some  about a specific
человек пришёл и с каким-то конкретным
language, but in order to have an understanding of how to
языком а чтобы было понимание как
build algorithms, how to translate a physical process into a program language,
строить алгоритмы как переводить на язык
so I want
физический процесс вот я хочу чтобы
something like this to
что-то как мне вот это чтобы что-то
explain something to a computer, there are
объяснить к компьютеру есть есть
some, and that's it,
какие-то и вот именно именно
programming gives an
программирование дает
understanding of an approach like this  you can do it and
понимание подход как это можно делать и
then it greatly simplifies the task in
потом это сильно упрощает задачу в при
digitalization during formation, and so, of
цифровизации при формировании так вот ну
course, I
и хочется конечно же
want students in the basic tools section to
чтобы студенты в разделе базовым
pay attention to what
инструментарием вниманием что такое
financial statements are about what they
финансовая отчетность про что она какие
are
бывают
with tools parameters coefficients of the
с инструменты параметры коэффициенты
model
модели как
how to analyze an investment project
как анализировать инвестиционный проект
in general why this is all  how they of course
вообще зачем это все как они конечно
basis basis is
базис базис нужен
needed here is a programmer
нужно вот это вот программистка
analytical
аналитическое
state well at least here at least it is
состоянии ну вот хотя бы вот хотя бы это
to get a bank 3 components are so
получить банк 3 составляющие такие
powerful I like a deacon take note
мощные я как дикон беру себе на заметку
that our students should at least
что наши студенты должны по крайней мере
pass what happens in different
сдать что бывает по разному
ways still another
разному еще еще
skill  learn skill skill get
умение учиться навык навык получать
fight analyze information
воевать анализировать информацию потому
because without this you can’t do without it
что без этого без этого нельзя
alexey plows thank you very much for the
алексей пашет большое спасибо за
comment, I propose to
комментарий я предлагаю на этом
end
закончить
our some official part with
нашу какую-то официальную часть
speeches and
выступлениями и
finally for those students
наконец-то для тех студентов которые
who stayed here,
которые здесь остались
maybe you wanted to ask something, we
возможно вы хотели что-то спросить у нас
turned out to be very full of such a one and a half
оказался очень насыщенный такое полтора
hours more than we thought, so if you
часа больше чем мы думали вот если у вас
have any questions with the speaker
есть какие то вопросы тем спикером
that we have left, then please, it
которые у нас остались то пожалуйста
's time to ask and I know that among
самое время задать и я знаю что еще у
our guests there is Andrey Karen check,
нас из гостей есть андрей карен чек
who develops financial
который развивает развивает финансовые
services in the field of personal finance,
сервисы в сфере персональных финансов
maybe Andrey that  - I wanted to
может быть андрей что-то хотел
add a general question to students not
добавить в общем вопрос к студентам не
current and in the future, do not hesitate to ask
текущем и будущем не стесняйтесь задать
some question of your own, we
какой-то свой вопрос вот мы с
will be happy to answer and maybe
удовольствием ответим и может быть
Andrey wanted to say something according to his
андрей что-то хотел сказать по его
impression, but from the side of
впечатление но со стороны вот сервисов
personal finance
персональных финансах
services, the area of centralization is also a good
тоже сфера централизации
veni
добрый вечер
g  well, I didn’t listen to a very interesting
ну не не послушал очень интересное
speech, of course, for all the skills
выступление конечно на все навыки
that are listed
которые перечисления востребован
necessary, the
необходимые
necessary ones will always come in handy not only in finance,
всегда пригодятся не только в финансах
but also in a simple life,
но и простой жизнью
specifically,
конкретно
even the top managers with
даже руководители самого высшего звена с
whom I communicate,
которыми общаюсь
for example, are now lost and cannot
например сейчас теряются и не могут
determine how to act in the conditions of
определить как же действовать в условиях
dynamically changing exchange rates
там динамично меняющихся курсов валют а
there, including for making their own
в том числе для принятия собственных
decisions, not only on a scale  businesses on the
решений не только в масштабах бизнеса в
scale of managing their own
масштабах управления своим собственным
capital, in this regard, the
вот в этом плане
use of
применение
effective there and
эффективных там и
various tools and techniques,
различных инструментов и методик том
including digital ones, especially digital ones, which
числе цифровых особенно цифровых которые
allow a long-term financial model
позволяют долгосрочной финансовой модели
or
либо
identify the most difficult
выявлять самый сложный
undefined places, including
не определенные места и в том числе
managing risks, they are actually in
управлять рисками они собственно
demand more than ever now
востребованы как никогда сейчас будет
because  that
потому что
more and more more the
все больше больше больше
environment in which we are
окружении который в котором мы находимся
at the moment it
на текущий момент она больше больше
changes more more more uncertainty
меняется больше больше неопределенности
and only
и только
tools for analysis of rapid
инструменты анализа быстрого
modeling,
моделирования
planning, assessment and risk management
планирования оценки и управления рисками
can, so to speak, lead
могут скажем так привести к
to  in a hurry, I would say so, but
успеху я бы так сказал а вот в том числе
including not
и не
only in business and managing
только в бизнесе и управления там
cash flows or assets there, but also with
денежными потоками либо активами но и
my own financial well-being
собственным финансовым благополучием
up to 3 thanks, absolutely what is called I
до 3 спасибо совсем что называется
completely agree,
совсем согласен даже
even now I would like to note such a moment
вот еще хотел бы такой момент отметить
that
что
here are a
вот
lot of specialties, a lot of
множество специальностей множество
plans I  reviewed the training and drew
планов я учебных пересмотрел и обратил
attention to the fact that, for example, he
внимание что он например
sees personal
видеть личным персональным финансами
wealth management as very little
управления благосостояния очень мало
attention, and for example, if in the
уделяется внимания и например если в
programs of Western universities there, let’s say
программах там западных вузов допустим
career planning is an
карьерное планирования является как
integral part of personal
составной части управления личного
wealth management, we have this item, but
благосостояния это у нас этот пункт а
somehow it is very missed and in fact  business,
как-то очень пропускается и по сути дела
for example, resume writing skills, it’s
например навыки написания резюме он
not at all where, it’s
вообще не где никогда же не
never covered, or there are some, but
ну не освещается либо там какие-нибудь а
writing even when you already need to write a
написание даже когда уже нужно писать
resume when, yes, yes, that is, when
резюме когда да да то есть когда уже
Andrei Novotorgovy is already laid down by a lack of
андрей новоторговый заложен недостатка
personal finance, it seems to me that this is another
личных финансов мне кажется это еще
kind of cultural barrier  there is
какой-то культурный барьер есть в том
that but I'm going to  and as if there is no
что но я собираюсь свой как бы нет ворот
gate somehow to increase my net worth
свою как-то чистую стоимость увеличить
during my career and how to say I
за время карьеры и как сказать этим
do it somehow systematically and
занимаюсь как-то планомерное и
how to say
как сказать
systematically, in my opinion it has not yet
систематически вот у нас по моему еще не
taken root, well, the idea and it seems to me that this is a
прижилось это ну идея и мне кажется это
drawback that we really need this
недостаток что мы ну этим нужно
do it and the earlier
действительно заниматься и чем раньше ты
you invest more in it how to
инвестируешь этим большую тебя как
say the
сказать
result by the time of retirement how
результат к моменту выхода на пенсию как
really very important such
действительно очень важные такие
moments
моменты
there are things but really need
есть предметы но действительно нужно
more thank you for showing and the
больше что спасибо что показали и
numbers
числа
[music]
[музыка]
sergey
сергей
I also want to talk to our guests
я хочу еще вот разговорить наших гостей
if they are still in flocks
если они еще стаями
sergey anatolievich is love
сергей анатольевич is love
for
руководители акционеры смотрят на
some period of
какой-то период
about a year until now  maybe even
порядка года до сейчас может быть даже
less and does not see the return
меньше и не видит отдачи
on investments of
от вложений
digitalization a lot of finance function with
цифровизации масса финансов функция с
this you constantly encounter such a
этим постоянно сталкиваешься такая вот
pain, probably many financiers
боль наверное многих финансистов
seem to need it all the time, but the drive in the
вроде как все время нужно но драйв в
context of the year does not appear, so
разрезе года не проявляется поэтому
we put off the low priority and
приоритет низкие мы откладываем и
everyone needs it, but the film is how to say the
получает всем нужно но фильм как сказать
budget  the next year the
бюджет на следующий год не попадает
paradoxical situation of a milkmaid does not fall recently he
парадоксальная ситуация доярки недавно
talked with a colleague he is also engaged in the
общался с коллегой он занимается тоже
digitalization of the tariff area and when he
цифровизации области тарифов и когда он
talks about the bird with none of the clients at all,
расскажу о птице вообще ни с одним из
he asked him the question of what digitalization will give
клиентов тот ему задал вопрос что даст
me in this direction,
мне то цифровизации вот этом направлении
he answered him accuracy at the rocks yes if
тот ему ответил точность у скал да если
if you would say the
бы ты сказала
cost of the economy, I would not talk to you further,
стоимость экономика я бы с тобой дальше
but the fact that the accuracy is
на стал разговаривать но то что точность
increasing and I
увеличиваться и я для себя вот такой
chose such a vector for myself that it is precisely by
какой-то вектор выбрал что именно
avoiding some
избегая каких-то ошибок
mistakes, including accounting in budgeting, that
в том числе там в учете в бюджетировании
one can probably show the effectiveness of
можно наверно показывать эффективностью
digitalization of which  -the direction,
цифровизации каких-то направлению я бы
if possible, I would also test 2
при возможности еще протестировал 2
answers  this is flexibility and reliability, that
ответа это гибкость и надежность то есть
is, paralysis can go in different
за парализация может пойти до разными
ways, one of them is existing
путями один из них это существующие
processes, we even more how to say
процессы мы еще более как сказать
give a lot of
обвешивать большим количеством
automation this is one way and the other
автоматизации это один путь а другой
way is when we invest in
путь когда мы инвестируем в то чтобы
being able to reconfigure,
иметь возможность перенастроиться том
including chasing some kind of crisis  period
числе гнаться какой-то кризисный период
to which we better understand the
до что мы лучше понимаем структуру
cost structure better understand where
стоимости лучше понимаем где формируется
our costs are formed and what brings more
у нас затраты и что приносит больше
money such flexibility and reliability in the
денег такая гибкость а надежность в том
sense that mistakes may not be avoided,
смысле что ошибок возможно не избежать
but we can avoid some kind of
но мы можем избежать какого-то
repetition or something of mistakes, this is
повторения что ли ошибок вот
how you think your owner or  here is
как вы думаете ваш собственник или вот
your branch of flexibility reliability
вашей отрасли гибкости надежность
that the
что
direction is just for persuading
направление как раз для убеждения
managers, but here this is a question
руководители но тут это вопрос такой
that is not always possible to translate into a figure,
который в цифра не всегда возможно
that is, but only Peter
перевести то есть а вот только питер
said how would I formulate this one for myself
говорил как бы вот этот я для себя
as ro and bag-end here is the
сформулировал как ро и бэг-энда вот
profitability the profitability of
доходность доходность
investments in  its how to say systems
вложений в свои как сказать системы
that do not sell anything but
которые ничего не продают но
provide life  the activity of the
обеспечивают жизнедеятельность
enterprise is very difficult to calculate
предприятия очень сложно посчитать
it is difficult to prove it is
сложно доказать
interesting that we are the same here
интересно что мы здесь совпадаем
when big
когда большое
vyacheslav natalia
вячеслав наталия
if you listened to the end you probably
если вы дослушали вы наверняка у вас
have something to say
есть что-то сказать
confirm or deny something
подтвердить или отрицать что-то
thanks
спасибо
doctor both of this
доктор оба этого
[music]
[музыка]
I am glad that you could join and yes
я рад что вы смогли присоединиться и да
I  I was worried that we could
я переживал что мы не ту ссылку могли
send him the wrong link, move a straight wide range of
прислать его двиньте прям широкий спектр
opinions from the fact that one with this is the basis of the
мнений от того что один с это основа
basics to the fact that none of the happiness and
основ до того что ни в один из счастья и
need to develop other systems for us are
нужно развивать другие системы для нас
very well useful, it seems to me a look and
очень ну полезные мне кажется взгляд и
there are colleagues with whom you can discuss
есть коллеги с которыми можно обсуждать
different directions, it seems to me that this is the
разные направления мне кажется вот та
work that you are doing to participate in the
работа которую вы делаете по участию в
competition in
конкурсе в
teaching 1c, it just evokes a
преподавании 1с она прям вот вызывает
response and
отклик и
an important direction that requires
важное такое направление которое требует
knowledge in order to create an alternative
знания чтобы создать альтернативная
system, you need to know how the existing one
система нужно знать как существующую
works
работают
[music]
[музыка]
I already understood that
я это уже поняла что
financial documentation should be compiled
документацию финансовый составлять
[  music]
[музыка]
let's go deeper
будем углубляться
and yes, it seems to me that the base of the base is
да и есть мне кажется баз баз база
good and that's it  bring some of these
хорошая и вот привести часть этих
companies, including those for bachelor's
компаний в том числе на бакалаврские
programs, to some kind of but update
программы до какой-то но обновить
some courses with the participation of an
какие-то курсы с участием
industrial partner, you are one of those
индустриального партнера вот из тех ты
companies present here is quite
из компании присутствующих здесь вполне
real such a development of events
реальный такое развитие событий
you can try to ask things collect
можно попробуйте спросить вещи собери
yes yes
да да
try ask the numbers you search search
попробуй спросите числа вы ищи ищи
Vyacheslav Repina,
репина
did you listen to the end, do you want to
вячеслав вы дослушали хотите ли что-то
say something, what kind of remark is
сказать какая та реплика
apparently not and
видимо нет и
Vladimir, it seems to me that we have achieved the goal of
владимир на мне кажется мы достигли цели
our seminar, all those who were
нашего семинара все кто тех кого
invited
пригласили
expressed a lot, how do you like your
высказались есть много как вам ваши
impressions, how do you see our
впечатления как вам видится наша
future work, first of all, of course, I
дальнейшая работа во первых конечно
want to say a big thank you  to everyone who
хочется сказать большое спасибо всем кто
came to us today, this is a very valuable
пришел сегодня к нам это очень ценное
opinion, I noticed interesting things for myself
мнение для себя отметила на интересные
, now I’m working as part of the
вещи вот сейчас работой в рамках
admission campaign of working with applicants
приемной кампании работы с абитуриентами
who come from the program, I
которые приходят на от программы
noticed this trend, too, there is a
заметила такую тенденцию тоже происходит
certain transformation transformation of the
некая трансформация трансформация
request from students what was in the
запроса от студентов то что был в
past year before last  today they are already
прошлом-позапрошлом году сегодня это уже
students though  very attractive for them
студенты хотят и для них привлекательную
when I start to tell that the
очень когда я начинаю рассказывать что в
program has a large number of experts, a
программе большое количество экспертов
large number of people who are
большое количество людей которые
directly involved in business, a
непосредственно занимаются бизнесом
large number of cases, but for them this
большое количество кейсов но для них это
is now a very important
является сейчас очень таким важным
attractive moment, and for many
привлекательным моментом и и у многих
it is the decision to
именно решение созревает подать
apply for our program after
документы на нашу программу после того
when you don’t hear that there is an
когда не услышать что здесь есть
expert position here, that there are people here
экспертная позиция что здесь есть люди
who will tell you about the things that are
которые расскажут те вещи которые
happening now in business, and that’s the
происходят сейчас в бизнесе и вот тот
request that we heard today, it really
запрос что мы сегодня услышали он очень
responds to students for them, it’s important,
отзывается у студентов для них это важно
today I saw that we are moving towards
я сегодня увидел что мы идем навстречу
each other, it’s great  I give it great that
друг другу это здорово я даю здорово что
the experts themselves and business representatives
сами эксперты и представители бизнеса
say that we need students who have
говорят что нам нужны студенты которые
tried one, two, three things and already how
попробовали одну две три вещи и уже как
can they tell some independent
они могут какую-то самостоятельную
position, it’s very cool,
позицию рассказать это очень здорово
we will be glad to see everyone on our
будем будем рады видеть всех на наших
programs within our disciplines
программах внутри наших дисциплин в
as guest speakers of the central
качестве гостевых спикеров центральных
spike  I
спикеров этого здоровая с большим таким
’m looking forward to the start of our program with such great enthusiasm,
воодушевлением жду начала старта нашей
I think that it will be something
программы я думаю что это будет что-то
special,
особенное
thank you very much for them, mutual
спасибо большое вам за им взаимного
thanks to colleagues for participating, thanks to our
спасибо коллеги за участие спасибо нашим
guests, we are
гостям
waiting for applicants in our
ждем абитуриентов на нашей программе
program  goodbye guests
уважаемые гости до свидания